Heat. Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome Welcome back to the Ask
Abijit Show. Today we are doing episode
325. I hope you're all doing great.
There's a lot that's happening in the
world. I'm sure there's a lot to
discuss. I'm sure there's a lot of
questions you all have. So, so before we
get into the questions, let's see who
all is there in the live chat with us
tonight. Precious talks, Anish 24,
Bascar Bandit, Har Banana Higard. Okay.
Um Har Banana Higard is here from
Jarkand. Good to see you, sir. Good to
see you geopolitical dub. Good evening
as always from Indor. Um
Sachin GK Sachin GK General Subutai.
General Subhutai is here. Adwani Shri
Dabv
is here from Odisha. Good to see you
sir. Nabad Das Shri D once again from
Pune. Abupar Utkash Shukla. Nirvana
Shanks Kuni Chiva sir Konicha good to
see you. Uh Swami
Maklebin is also here with us. Uh
Abishek Shukla live animals for for
laugh is here from Mumbai. Uh soldier
boy is also here. Meow meow indeed. User
U7V8V.
Abuai Singh Jay Jamudep. Abisheka live
from Kpur.
Uh Manhattan says there are earthquakes
in Iran. I think we're going to have to
look at it. Swami Jin is here from
Jaipur. John M. Funk is here. Manhattan
is also talking about earthquake in in
Iran. Amish, good evening ma'am. Uh user
7. Yes, Anish Bharat Ram Ram G. Ram
Maklav Jay Bajang Bali. Uh Swami, do I
like Frank Sinatra songs? I not bad.
Yeah, some of them are great. I'm sure.
Uh Manhattan Animals for laugh 6552.
Chandu Shkr7733
is here from Peshawar, India. Peshawar,
India. Good evening uh General Subutai
once again. Are you seeing pranam sarji?
Pranam sarg uh Shubhham Ja. Hello Manish
Shakaru. Namaste G. Namaste ma'amashish
Samal. Hello. Uh who else do we have?
Ganesh Desh Pande. Rahul Rahul is here.
Hello Rahul G.
Uh what else do we have? Who else do we
have? We have Utkar Shukla once again.
Mac 4 J1U Amit Pande good evening Mohit
Takar hello Vijay Vagila good evening
Ganesh Desh Pandai Ritik Pawar
um Ashish
Nahit
Nahabhai
Nahabhai Nahabhai Guru okay namaste uh
uh who else we have user U7 V8V from
Kerala good evening good evening and
everybody else good evening so uh let us
get going with the questions. First of
all, there's this uh talk about uh
earthquakes
in Iran. Are we are we So, Manhattan
says there are many earthquakes in Iran.
Do they have nukes? I haven't seen these
reports, but let us let us now quickly
get to the bottom of this if we can in a
in a couple of minutes. Uh Iran
earthquake.
Do we have any Iran? Sorry, not Iran.
Iran.
Do we have multiple earthquakes?
Um 99 earthquakes in Iran in just one
week. Okay, that's what Infforts is
saying. And there are YouTube uh videos
about 99 earthquakes in one week. Uh do
we have USGS? What does USGS have to say
about this? Let's see. Um this is 2026
123. That's a couple of days ago.
And yeah, not not a lot here. Do we have
a list of earthquakes in Iran? Wikipedia
as always is not necessarily a good
source of information, but let's see.
Um, it's going all the way to 9 2000 BC
or something. Okay, nothing much here.
Once again, um, what does this have to
say? Earthquake. USGS.gov. Once again,
the same thing. Okay, so I'm not sure
where this story is coming from. In
shorts, I'm not sure how reliable it is.
Hindustan Times is a reasonably
reliable, I suppose, piece of uh source
of information, I suppose. Uh surge of
seismic activity in Iran.
Just a paragraph or something. Okay,
that's not a lot. So I I'm not sure how
reliable these claims are. Not sure. But
uh I'll keep an eye on this. I'll keep
an eye on this. Okay. So then let us go
and take the first super chat. We have
Basar Bandit. Pyth indeed sir. Uh yes
I'm good. How I hope you're doing great
too. Uh so the Chinese Communist Party
has just arrested Jang Yushia uh CDS
equivalent in Indian army chief of
defense services chief of defense staff
kind of. Yeah equivalent. So how does a
power fight and find replacements if
they keep sacking lieutenant generals
and major generals? So it looks like
this is part of uh the power struggle.
Looks like, you know, there's
indications, there's speculation that
maybe there was some kind of coup
attempt in Beijing, right? That's the
speculation that's making the rounds in
social media, etc. Right now, not just
in social media, but also among
well-informed people, think tanks and
analysts and so on. Looks like there
could have been a coup attempt against
Xiinping probably done by looks like
Shangu Yusa and he has been u arrested
removed and uh strong condemnation has
been put out um uh in Chinese official
communications
u of Jang Joshua
and uh yeah looks like a purge has
happened and uh in the past several
months plenty of Chinese high-ranking
general etc. have been um you know
removed from uh service, arrested. So
looks like Xiinping is is ensuring that
no one in the PLA so-called PLA people's
liberation army uh is allowed to stay in
power. Anyone who who could potentially
be opposed to him u and this looks like
the latest in that. So um a lot of
people have been purged. A lot of
highranking generals and commanders have
been purged out of the uh people's
liberation army under the orders of Shri
X Shiinping right so what happens when
you remove such high ranking officers
what happens I mean how do you replace
them right I mean Jang Yua Yusa is one
of the final last people left in the PA
who had actual combat exper experience
the 1979 Vietnam war. Let's quickly
Google this guy, Jang Yushua. Okay, Jang
Yu Shia.
So, what does Wikipedia have to say
about him?
He was 75 years old and he um
did he Yeah. So, he did he took part in
the Sino Vietnamese war of 1979, right?
And also battle of Laoshan
between Yeah. All that. So he was one of
the last remaining uh top commanders in
the PLA who had actually seen military
combat. China hasn't fought a war since
the 1979 war against Vietnam which China
lost which China initiated and China was
beaten back right. China got a bloody
nose in that. So China lost that and
after that China hasn't fought any
actual conflict any actual war and this
guy was one of the last you know high
top ranking people who had served in it.
So now you have the entire PLA uh top
carder, top top brass, uh if you see
them, they haven't really seen combat.
They haven't really seen warfare. So
they're essentially they may be
experienced in terms of seniority and
and so on, promotions and all, but they
haven't seen warfare. They haven't seen
combat. So that's what we have. So what
happens when you sack people like these?
How do you replace them? Well, you
replace them with a bunch of people.
There's always a large pool of officers
who come below them right in the rank in
the rank hierarchy. So you can always
promote somebody who is loyal to
Xiinping and who has reasonably good uh
a good reasonably good track record um
in the PLA. I mean obviously track
record when we're talking about track
record here we're not talking about uh
combat track record because there's no
combat track record uh since 1979. But
you know people who have done the right
things and u dedicated disciplined
obedient loyal to the Chinese communist
party loyal to Xiinping thought all
that. So you you know you raise people
like those and what it gives you is a p
top brass that is well inexperienced in
combat but that's what you have. So
looks like there's a lot of uh stuff
happening behind the scenes in Beijing
in China. It looks like Xiinping is uh
consolidating his his position and
fighting off any potential challengers
and looks like there could have been
some kind of attempted coup which is why
this guy was rapidly you know suddenly
removed and a very rapid condemnation
was put out in Chinese official
government communicate
right so that's what's going on in China
maybe it's good news for Taiwan you know
uh basket bandit says is Singapore a
Chinese vasal or a US vasal allegedly.
Does it also act as a moneyaundering
place like London or Dubai? Well, we
know that London definitely is the
global epicenter of money laundering.
It's also the place where uh you know
former uh dictators etc go to go to
retire and so on. People who have served
the west that sort of people right uh
so that's the kind of place it is
London. What about Singapore? Uh I don't
know about Dubai moneyaundering and all
that. I'm not aware of that. Uh but what
about Singapore? So Singapore is kind of
the London of the East essentially uh
especially as as a major financial hub
in in the eastern hemis well London is
also technically the eastern hemisphere
I suppose but in in Asia you know in the
Asia-Pacific region you have Singapore
that's a major uh financial center. I
once again I'm not sure about whether
there's any moneyaundering or whatever
happening out of Singapore. Singapore
obviously is is very much allied or
aligned with the west. So I'm sure that
sometimes you may have Chinese warships
that may dock at Singapore port but uh
Singapore is very much aligned with the
west not with China. it has good
relations with China and the Chinese
Communist Party has actually studied
Singapore in great detail um
in order to understand how to transform
a nation and how to bring about the
reforms that make a nation a great
power. The Singapore can't be a great
power. It's just a city state. But Ding
Shopping used to send uh CCP, Chinese
Communist Party officials to Singapore
to study how they have u you know
structured their government and how they
carried out reforms that transformed
Singapore in just one generation from
third world to first world and they
implemented that the Chinese they
they've been you know u they deeply
admire Singapore and obviously Singapore
is dominated by Chinese origin people.
So you have these factors that
definitely um show us commonalities
between Singapore and China. But
Singapore is very much aligned with the
west. You have American aircraft
carriers that routinely dock in
Singapore. Routinely, I mean reasonably
routinely dock in Singapore. U so
Singapore, if you want to designate
Singapore as a vasal, it definitely is
not a Chinese vasal. Um, of course,
Singapore has, you could say Singapore
is kind of a US facile. Singapore has of
course stood up for itself when it comes
to u, you know, not bending to American
dictats and whims. For example, there
was the famous famous caning case,
right? Uh, Singapore U Singapore
caning
caning uh, yes, caning of Michael Fay.
So there was this guy in 1994 you know
American teenager who was sentenced to
be lashed six times with a cane for
violating some rules right vandalism act
and the American government protested
they said that you can't do this and
Singapore said go to hell we're going to
can him and they caned him so you know
Singapore has kind of stood up for
itself in this small matters uh let's
see this one this also do Chinese
warships
dock
dock in Singapore I'm pretty Sure they
do. Yes, Chinese warships do dock in
Singapore, right? Do regularly dock in
Singapore. So Singapore is
it's not a Chinese vasal. It has good
relations with China, but it's if you
want to well, if you want to assign
vasal hood, it's definitely more of a US
facile. Okay. Pascar Bandit says, "Why
do ordinary Europeans seem so naive
about the US being the dominant power in
the EU?"
Many on social media act as if Poland
and Denmark are bravely standing up to
US bullying
and they denied Trump Greenland and what
not. Look, most people believe whatever
they are taught.
I don't expect uh European textbooks to
teach kids that you know what we are not
sovereign nations.
Our sovereignty has been taken away by
the US. Our big boss, our overlord is
the US. That's what you will I don't
expect any European nation to teach this
to their kids in schools. They're going
to tell kids that you know our country
is great. We have the rule of law. We
have laws. We are part of the EU. Blah
blah blah blah blah. they will not
mention any of this. I mean look at what
you have in Japan. Most Japanese people
are super pacifist because they have
been taught in school that Japan is a
terribly violent evil nation that
deserves to be punished for its sins and
the Americans are this great benevolent
power that has placed Japan under its
protection and Japan has forever
forceworn the use of military force and
all of that. Right? And uh because of
what they are taught, the Japanese kids
are completely oblivious to the fact
that Japan has it hosts more than 130
permanent US military bases on its soil.
It's under permanent US military
occupation. Despite this being there
right in front of their eyes, they don't
realize that they are not a sovereign
country. They are an occupied country.
Eventually, once you reach a certain
age, you may start questioning that. But
most people don't question anything.
Most people just want to be told what to
think and they are happy with that.
Thinking is hard work. Thinking thinking
hurts the brain. Why think?
Just live in this happy illusurary
world. So that's the thing. I'm sure
there are Europeans who understand
what's happening. But the ordinary
European person will be oblivious to
what's going on, you know, and that's
that that's that's how the world works.
That's that's the facade of democracy
and all that.
Bascar Bandit says, "Please elaborate on
how the panuran corridor can allegedly
benefit our ally nation Israel. As we
discussed this one area where Bharat,
Iran together are with Armenia against
Turkey, Azarbaijan and and the prior the
prior. Okay. Okay. Let's go to the map.
Okay. We since we are discussing the pan
corridor
um yeah okay so let's open the map.
And we're going to discuss the pan
corridor and first of all understand
what part of the world we're talking
about here. So we are talking about
since we're talking about Turkey.
See if you look at central Asia. Yes you
have nations like Kazakhstan,
Usbekiststan, Kygystan, Turkmanistan.
U
also well Chinese occupies occupied East
Turkiststan etc. All these nations are
Turic nations. Okay. Their people speak
Turk languages and they have a Turk
ethnicity. Turk ethnicity mixed with
some Indoskitian ethnicity which is
older but that's what it is. So these
are all Turk nations and to the west we
have uh Azarbaijan which is not part of
Central Asia. It's part of the caucases.
It's also a Turk nation. And then to the
further to the west bypassing Armenia
leaprogging Armenia we have Turkey.
So if we go east of Turkey, if you just
disregard Armenia, you have Azarbaijan,
then the Caspian Sea, then a bunch of
Turk nations. Now in olden days, the
Turk nations, this territory was called
Tan.
Tran. So the great dream of Turkey is to
essentially erase Armenia from the map
of the world.
Have Azarbaijan take over Armenia or
maybe have Armenia's territory split
into Turkey and Azharbaijan. Okay. And
then create this corridor that stretches
all the way from essentially Anatolia
Turkey through Azarbaijan
over the Caspian Sea into this Turk
region large Turk region. Turkmanistan
Usbakistan, Tajakistan, sorry not
Tajakistan, Tajakistan is Iranian,
Indo-ranian, Kygystan, Kazakhstan, all
these Turk nations. So that is the idea
of this pan corridor. This great Turk
corridor, this broad region in central
Asia
that essentially is entirely Turk in in
ethnicity and culture and language. The
only issue is Armenia. So that's why
Armenia the Turks want to solve Armenia
by essentially wiping Armenia out and
finish what they started in 1915. So
that's the pan corridor. Okay. So if the
pan corridor happens then Turkey has
unfettered access all the way into
central Asia all the way to Kyrgystan
uh and and Kazakhstan. Kazakhstan it
borders essentially almost Mongolia
that's how far east it reaches and this
region obviously it has plenty of uh
natural resources oil gas Kazakhstan
etc. uh lots of mineral resources and so
on and uh so it's it's a pretty uh you
know uh lucrative
region from the natural resources
viewpoint and for Turkey it's obviously
Turkey likes to position itself as the
leader of the Turk world. So if can if
it can connect with the Turkey world, it
will uh you know give Turkey more power,
prestige, resources, all of that. And
Turkey obviously has dreams of reviving
the Ottoman caliphate kind of thing. So
neo-toman ambitions. So that's why the
Panther corridor is the dream of Turkey.
Now how does it benefit other nations?
So how does it benefit the US for
example? So as as we discussed you know
this region the central Asia region is
rich in natural resources and Turkey is
a member of NATO it's a US ally US vasal
even though it has imperial ambitions of
its own. So if Turkey can control these
nations and have access to this entire
region that it benefits the US straight
away, right? because US can also u you
know tap into this region also it it uh
kind of uh if this region comes under
Turk and American domination then it's a
challenge for China as well as Russia
because Russia likes to think of Central
Asia Asia as as its uh uh region of you
know region of interest region of
dominance but if Turkey becomes do
dominant in the region it's a challenge
for Russia as well as China has this
belt and road initiative that it seeks
to expand through Central Asia. It's not
working anymore. The the project is kind
of dead. But it's a further challenge to
China, right? Because China also seeks
the resources in Central Asia. Uh now
what about Israel? So Israel as as we
have discussed in the past, Israel is an
ally of Azarbaijan and Azarbaijan and
Turkey are mortal enemies of Armenia and
India and Iran are supporting Armenia.
So India is is essentially supporting a
nation that Israel is opposing. So,
Israel and India are on opposing sides
when it comes to this conflict.
Azaranjan, Armenia. Uh, so Iran and
India are supporting Armenia. Now, if
this pan corridor happens, how does it
help Israel? So, first of all, why is
Israel supporting Azarbaijan? Well, two
reasons. First of all, Israel is
purchasing Azar Azarbaijani energy, oil
and gas, right? In reasonable
quantities, large quantities, I suppose.
That's one reason. The second reason is
that you know if you look at Iran,
Iran's northwestern region is the
Azarbaijan province and the people here
are ethnic Azarbaijanis. So if Iran can
um you know if if Iran is an ally of
Azarbaijan then it can use the
Azarbaijani population in Iran to keep
an eye on what's happening in Iran and
possibly do a you know in the future
some kind of regime change operation if
that is even possible. So that's why
Israel is aligned or allied with
Azarbaijan and if the pan corridor
becomes a thing then Israel can you know
Azarbaijan becomes more relevant more
powerful and Israel can uh tap and and
and this is a challenge then for for
Iran also because Iran and Turkey are
you could say adversaries.
So if Turkey becomes dominant in central
Asia, that's a major challenge for Iran
also. And that's obviously is an
indirect good thing for Israel. So
multiple reasons why Israel can benefit
from a pan corridor happening. I'm sure
the Israelis have no ill will towards
the Armenian people, but well, it is
what it is. National interest comes
first.
Basker Bandit says, "We discuss often
how ISRO is underfunded, but what
benefits can BAT have by developing an
equivalent to the James Web or the
Hubble Space Telescope? Any benefits
that will add not only to astronomy but
military?" See, why does the US spend so
much on NASA? Why does it spend so much
on these uh projects like like Hubble,
like the James Web Space Telescope? Why
does it spend so much money on these uh
uh on these spacecraft like New Horizons
that you know did a flyby of Pluto 11
years ago and it's still going out into
outer space. What about the Pioneer
missions? Pioneer 1, Pioneer 2, the
Voyager missions, the Voyager spacecraft
are now out uh into outer space beyond
um essentially out of the solar system.
Why does the US spend so much money on
these things? What's there? What's the
point?
What's the point? Why does the US spend
so much money on things like uh things
like uh LIGO,
right? The gravitational wave detector
costs so much money. What do you get out
of this? You get scientific expertise,
engineering expertise, technological
expertise. All of these things have
spin-offs in so many different areas.
So many different areas. For example,
space. If if you want to put something
like the JWST James web space telescope
into the what into one of the lagj
points the one that's behind the earth
in the earth's shadow well you need to
have high quality a high quality space
program to do that of course they use
the the French rocket for that aryan but
whatever so first of all to do all these
projects you need to have a high quality
space program which means you need a
high quality engineering uh pool of
talent which means you need to develop a
high quality education system for that
and R&D and all that right. So just to
put this thing into orbit you need high
quality engineers and those engineers
they will they obviously work on space
rockets and all they can also work work
on missiles and that those engineering
skills can be applied to any engineering
work right then you have um if you have
JWST James web space telescope all the
way you know millions of kilometers away
and you need to get signals from from
that you need to have extremely high
quality telemetry
okay uh telecommunications equipment. So
you need to develop that that has other
if other spin-offs into all kinds of
military applications or other
applications, right? So the space
program itself has had so many spin-offs
that had that have you know military
applications that essentially you can't
imagine. So all these things just by
having just by developing things like
this you you're forced to develop
technologies that have applications in
lots of other domains including the
military domain. So let's say India okay
BAT develops uh let's say u u something
like the James James web space
telescope. So that's a massive massive
machine to launch that just into orbit
you need a probably a rocket that's more
powerful than the most powerful rocket
India has.
I'm sure the PSLV or the GSLV or
whatever LMV3 whatever I'm sure it can't
take what's the what's the JWST's launch
mass? Let me see.
Okay, let's see quickly. Uh, JW
ST launch mass. What was the launch
mass? 6,000 something kilogram. 6.1
tons. Okay. Uh, LVM
preload
capacity
4,000 of the GGS uh, low earth orbit.
But we want this to go beyond low earth
orbit. We want this to not even go into
geosp synchronous track for orbit. We
need the the the
uh telescope to
essentially go into the lagrange point.
So you need to send it beyond the GTO.
So the Indian rocket simply can't do the
job. We don't have a powerful enough
rocket. So we have we'll have to develop
a more powerful rocket. Well there you
have augmented capabilities just to
launch this thing. Then we will need
telemetry. We'll need to have the
telecommunications. there are
capabilities that can actually
communicate with with this thing in near
real time as as close to real time as
possible. So you need and and to develop
a a telescope of that that quality you
know with those hexagonal you know uh
elements in its uh mirror and all of
that you need to develop high quality
optics and whatnot which obviously if
you can develop high quality optics you
can have military applications of that.
So all of these things they may look
like wasteful expenditure but you know
the the technological capabilities you
develop by building these things they
have applications everywhere. We only
see just one linear thing that you know
we are building a telescope but do you
know um
the US military at some point in time
donated two uh telescopes space
telescopes to NASA okay because they
were redundant and they the US military
didn't did not need those those were spy
telescopes and each of those telescopes
was more powerful in terms of
capabilities than the Hubble space
telescope
so something like Hubble that is turned
towards the stars if you turn it towards
the
imagine what it can do, right? Or or
something similar to Hubble. So that's
the point. These things are everything
is interconnected. Just by developing
missions like these, you can you'll
develop a pool of talent and set of
capabilities that have applications in
all kinds of different fields,
especially the military field. Rocketry
and missiles are the same thing.
Telescopes and spy cap spy satellite
capabilities are the same thing
essentially, right? telecommunications,
telemetry, all of that you need that in
the military domain and all the
electronics and whatn not you develop
will also be used in the military
domain. All of this comes together
right but we in India don't have this
understanding possibly or maybe we don't
have the ambition that's why ISRO is
just underfunded and I don't know what's
happening
Pawar says are we back in the era where
the strong will eat up the weak
when did we ever leave that era in the
past things were done nicely today
things are done brashly you know Donald
Trump is throwing around his weight like
like a wildfire in a library right like
an elephant in a garden.
But the US has always done this. In the
past, they've done it diplomatically.
They have not shown, they've not
flaunted their power, but they've always
done the same things.
I mean, after in the 1990s, what did
they do do to Yugoslavia?
What was it? It was brutal. Was it not
the time when the strong ate up the
weak? Yugoslavia was weak. Its strong
protector, the USSR, had disintegrated.
So, what did the remaining strong guy,
the US do? ate up Yugoslavia, right? You
didn't see that the US did all these
regime change operations from the 2000s,
1990s, 2000s, all the way until now.
They recently I mean it's always been
this way, but in the past you you could
not see it. I could see it. I was
telling this for 4 years, but now you're
beginning to see it because now Trump is
making it very obvious.
It's always been the an era where the
strong eat up the weak. The 1990s it was
that 1980s, 1970s, '60s, it's always
been that way. The strong always eat up
the weak. But typically they do it
quietly behind the scenes. They do it
with diplomatic fides.
Diplomacy is is typically nice and
gentile and polite and sophisticated and
cultured. Today diplomacy is brash,
especially American diplomacy and
Chinese diplomacy. The Chinese have
toned it down. The Americans are very
brash now in the Trump era. But the
world has always been the same. The
world is unchanging.
The rules of power have never changed.
They're still the same.
VK Baja. Well, thank you so much, sir.
Thank you very much indeed.
Abishek Shivastav says, "History of
Germany, their culture, language,
origin, whole history. You want
you want their whole history?" Uh, look,
I can't give the whole history of
Germany. I will you can do like a 100
one-hour episodes for that. Uh but uh
history of Germany in in compressed time
scale. Uh the ger there there were a
bunch of Germanic tribes you know that
the Romans were aware of. So north of
the river Rin R H I N E. Would you like
to see the map of the Ryan? North of the
Ryan the German the the Romans called
that region Gmana Magna. Okay. Greater
Germany or whatever. See the Ryan River
is the border between Switzerland and
Germany. If you come here from the Buden
Sea, you will see this river the Ry this
river here. See
Ryan River. So this is the this river is
the border between Switzerland and
Germany. And the Romans considered the
lands north of the Ryan to essentially
be Germany, Germany Magna.
South of that you had the Celtic lands.
West of that you had Gaul Golish uh uh
which is Golish territory which is now
France. Okay. And north of the Rine you
had Gmanaga and there were a bunch of
Germanic tribes that the uh Romans were
aware of and they fought them and they
subjugated them to some extent but those
lands were terribly inhospitable in
inhospitable full of forests and bogged
down and all that and u so the Romans
kind of stayed out of it. They kind of
tried to subjugate the people but did
not quite work. you had 10 AD or 9 AD
you know um the battle of Tutberg forest
which was a disaster for Rome and so on
so you had Germanic tribes there mainly
you know pretty wild people and then
then Romans fought them on multiple
occasions and so on and then there's a
bit long long long history where Germany
um did not really matter and then you
had the Holy Roman Empire and it was
partially in Germany and so on and then
you have Gutenberg and all that and you
have Martin Luther in the mid in the
dark ages of Europe and that that gives
rise to the enlightenment Gutenberg and
Martin Luther and then in 1871 we have
the before 1871 you have hundreds of
Germanic Germanic principalities duchies
and all these little little what in
India we would call princely states.
Yeah. And then in 1871 for the first
time in ever first time in history this
entire territory was was united for the
first time ever by the great uh iron
chancellor um
he was Prussian and Germany became kind
of an embodiment of Prussia and that's
1871 the first ever unification of
Germany an artificial nation created out
of a bunch of principalities
uh and and unified under one language
there's a bunch of languages in Germany,
Germanic languages, but it was the one
language we call German was superimposed
on everything. And then you have Germany
you know taking off because they had a
worldclass probably best in its kind
education system which focused on
science and technology. And that's why
Germany gave us quantum mechanics and so
much more and obviously Germany became a
major industrial power and then you have
World War I World War II and that's
that's the end of Germany essentially
because Germany becomes occupied by the
Americans in 1945 and it has been ever
since. And there we have it.
Saswat aims says, "Was Isil involved in
2611 terror attacks? Many claim RSS were
traitors." I have no idea about these
things. I have never heard of any
Israeli involvement. I don't know any of
the speculations, so I can't say. Sorry.
Shubam V says, "Succession plan after
she power scramble in CCP." We just
discussed this. We have no idea what's a
succession plan after she Mr. Shiining
has no intention as far as I know of uh
of of giving up power. He wants a fourth
term as the president. They're obviously
see the Chinese Communist Party is this
cutthroat system. Cutthroat system.
Okay.
Only the most ruthless rise to the top
and survive. You have to be ruthless in
the Chinese Communist Party system. And
that's why they always have high quality
leadership, not soft, useless, weak
leaders. They have ruthless leaders
because the system is so ruthless. It's
so cutthroat. It's dog eat dog. And
Xiinping if you look at his rise
political rise he has left a trail of
opponents in his wake. So that's how it
is. So there's going to be you know Xin
if you are the Chinese president you
always have to be on your toes. You
always have to keep looking you know
behind your shoulder who what's everyone
doing? And that's that's the situation.
Uh so obviously looks like there's been
some kind of incident in the CCP maybe
some kind of coup attempt or something
and it's been foiled as far as we know
and that's why the general was uh
unceremoniously ousted and harsh
condemnation was issued in the Chinese
media. Uh but what's the succession plan
after? Well, how am I to know? China is
an opaque country. The Chinese Communist
Party system is super opaque. Whatever
plans exist, we are not supposed to
know. So we can only speculate. I have
no idea what's the succession plan after
she mlein says general class is angry at
BJP. We really need an alternative.
Yeah. The UGC thing right those horrific
draconian
uh the whatever it was you know see what
I'll say is this.
Our leaders keep saying that cast is a
big problem in India. Right? Cast is a
big problem in India. big problem in
India. So if cast is a big problem
problem in India, why don't you remove
cast from everything? Remove cast from
birth certificates. Remove cast from
school certificates. Remove cast from
every official document. Remove it.
Right? Make it irrelevant.
They won't do it. You go to a government
office, they will ask for your cast.
You go to a temple, nobody asks for your
cast. But they say that temples are cast
and government is secular.
So that's the situation. Now if you have
this problem cast problem and you claim
it's it's an inherent problem in in
society, remove it. But they're not
removing it. And uh on the instead of
removing it, they're creating this
permanent distinctions between
artificial divisions
oppressor and oppressed. So only certain
categories of people are the oppressed
and they are permanently oppressed and
certain categories of people are
permanent oppressors.
You're creating a permanent solution to
a temporary artificial imaginary
problem. Maybe not imaginary, maybe it
exists. Okay, let's let's say it exists.
So you're creating you're implementing a
permanent solution to a temporary
problem. A permanent solution to a
temporary problem becomes a permanent
problem. That's what's happening. And uh
it's unfortunate.
Net
stat grep says, "Are holograms
scientifically possible? A device
projecting 3D images in the air and
vacuum, not the spinning screen ones
that mimic a hologram.
Are holograms scientifically possible?"
Uh, a device projecting 3D images in the
air and vacuum.
Okay. 3D images in the air and vacuum,
not the spinning. Yeah, we have the
screen things in which we look and we it
looks like a hologram, right? It mimics
a hologram. You can see it from
different angles and yeah it looks like
it's a threedimensional thing, but it's
actually a two dimensional image and you
know it uses a trick of opt tricks of
optics to do that.
Now, can you have a device that actually
projects a three-dimensional
image into air? Well, you see, if you
want to project, you certainly can
project photons, light into the air, but
how do you have the photons create a
visually, you know, a static image
somewhere? You can create an image by
projecting light on a screen, but air is
not a screen. The vacuum is not a
screen. So, how do you have light
stop at a place and and essentially
being emitted from a fixed position from
a fixed location in three-dimensional
space which is air or vacuum um
scientifically possible? I haven't
thought about this. I'm sure tech this
is this is actually a technological
problem and
you certainly can make air emit
light by excite by by having excitation
of the air molecules or gas molecules.
Can you have vacuum emit light?
Vacuum contains light. Vacuum can't emit
light. You have pair production etc.
this quantum u field theoretical
phenomena but you can't have that
actually create light. So it may be
possible in air. It's just a it's just
an engineering issue. There's nothing
against the laws of physics that happens
in that a vacuum. It may be more
difficult. But I'm sure that also is a
problem that can be solved through
engineering. So I would say there's
nothing in the laws of physics that that
prevents
such phenomena you know prevents you
from having such such an effect. But how
to solve it how how to solve the problem
how to make it happen that is something
that needs to be thought about. So I
think scientifically it should be
possible. There's nothing in the laws of
physics that prevents this from being
being possible but engineering obviously
it is a difficult problem to solve but
not unsolvable.
Basar mandit says during and post
operation Sindur we saw these
earthquakes in temporary nation Pakistan
as well just as now in Iran. What can
such a thing signify allegedly? Well,
see, I took a look at the time I mean a
few months ago, I took a look at those
earthquakes that had happened in in May,
right? In Pakistan. Uh let's let's see
if we can pull up that data. Yeah.
Earthquakes in Pakistan May 2025.
Uh earthquakes
in what is this
in Pakistan May 2025. Do we have data?
Let's see. Do we have data? USGS or
whatever earthquake today. Earthquake
today. Uh Substack earthquake insights.
Um
do we have USGS?
Do we have that? No. Okay. Let's see.
Um this is February 25. I said May,
right?
Let's see. I'm sorry. I don't mean to
yell at Google. So this is when when did
this up? Okay, this is January. The
point is what I'm trying to say. Okay.
List of earthquakes in 2025. Do we have
any
Okay, let's not say geological data.
Okay. Data
volcano discovery.
Um, once again, we don't have official.
I'm not sure which is the Okay. Do we
have earthquake list?
Okay. Complete Pakistan earthquake
report. Okay. Uh, location, location,
location. This is January 20. This is
today. Hell no.
Uh
map of latest earthquakes in near
Pakistan.
So can I Yeah. magnitude 2 plus major
only all earthquakes. Latest earthquake.
Can I filter by by
date? I suppose I can't.
240 yearly.
So once again, I'm not sure. Uh can I go
back?
Let's see. Let's see. Let's see. Do we
have any other data? What's volcano
discovery?
So do we. Okay. May 31, May 31, May 30,
May 30, May 24. Okay, we have let's say
May May 13, for example. This is
Afghanistan. This is Balut Baluchistan.
Let's see info. What info do we have?
How deep was the earthquake? Depth 10
km. So look at this. This is the point
I'm making. This earthquake
happened at a depth of 10 kilometers.
Now humans typically can't dig to a
depth of 10 km. Let's say you let's say
we are aware of the fact that if you
detonate a nuclear weapon underground,
it shows up in seismic seismograph
records as a low intensity earthquake.
And you can pinpoint essentially if you
have multiple seismographs where it
happened and how deep it happened. So
typically when you do an underground
nuclear test you may do it a few hundred
meters underground
maybe a kilometer underground. Let's
let's ask Google uh you know uh at
what depth
are underground nuclear
nuclear tests conducted. What depth?
Okay. So, yeah, depth of 200, 26, 800 m,
maybe a kilometer, right? Like I was
saying,
but these earthquakes that we're talking
about, they typically happen at a depth
of like multiple kilometers, 10 km, 12
km, maybe more. That can't be human in
origin.
That can't be nuclear
detonations
unless these reports are lying to us.
And you know, that's also a possibility.
Maybe the earthquake happened at at a
maybe the the event happened at a depth
of 800 mters but they are saying 10 km
they're lying that's also possible but
based on the open source information
that we have those bunch of earthquakes
around May that typically happened at
significant depths typically depths that
human beings humans don't reach the
deepest hole ever dug was about 9 10
kilometers right
so uh unless the the data is
manufactured unless the data is
falsified Those were not nuclear tests.
Now what I'm seeing in Iran, I'm not
sure. I mean, I took a look a while ago
at the latest earthquake data in Iran. I
was not able to find much. So, I think
we'll just wait and watch and see how is
how it's going.
Right.
Amisha says, "Can um you should write a
book on the Arian picnic myth." I
should, shouldn't I? Yeah. Yeah. I've
got multiple multiple books in here. Now
I'm in the process of slowly,
laboriously, tediously bringing them
out. So yes, I will certainly write a
book on this arin pit myth eventually. I
have a couple of books that need to come
out first. So I'm working on those
first. But yes, thank you for the
reminder. I have multiple people
reminding me of this. Some people remind
me of this every day. So Amish, thank
you to you two for reminding me. I
certainly will. I certainly will.
uh top seven whit says blunders of
burkad were with kgill 201611 see
look
my regular viewers know I don't speak
about internal politics in India okay I
stay out of this matters we all know
what happened
but u I I will stay out of this matter I
speak about three things history
geopolitics and science I don't discuss
Indian politics and this comes in Indian
politics actually even though it's
actually journalism but uh it's
political in nature so I will not
discuss these things right but I think
we all know so
Rohan says RSS
had talked about creating a new cast
system in Kolkata PC if you had to make
a system where there can never be
discrimination how will it be look I
will not discuss Indian politics um all
these matters are internal matters of
India Like I said, uh but if I had to
make a system where there can be never
be discrimination,
I will not be able to make such a
system. There can never be a system
where there is no discrimination. Never.
Never. Impossible.
You imagine that outside India all the
systems are without discrimination. You
think in the US there's no
discrimination. You think in Finland
there's no discrimination. You think in
other western countries there's no
discrimination.
There can never be a society where zero
discrimination exists.
You are all to taught by the Indian
education system that the Indian system
is horrible. The Indian culture is
horrible. Hinduism is horrible. Indian
civilization etc is horrible and
everything else is is is ideal.
You know that's how they make you hate
yourselves and your ancestors. That's
how they put this inferiority complex in
your heads.
I'm not saying the current Indian system
is great. I I think it's terrible. It's
terrible. Okay.
But if you want to create a system where
a society where there's no
discrimination,
you will never be able to create the
society. No matter what rules you
implement, no matter how many safeguards
you put in, you will either have a
draconian dictatorship which itself will
be discriminatory or it simply won't
work. Right?
So,
I mean the Taliban, have you seen what
they've done recently?
Have you seen what the Taliban has done
recently? I mean, I'm not sure if this
report is true or not, but let me uh
pull it up. Let me pull up this report.
I'm not sure if it's true or not, but
it's it's rather funny to see. Okay, so
give me a second.
Let me go to our friend Twitter. Okay,
now
look at this. So, this is a report from
this Twitter account. I'm not sure how
true it is. Okay, it says the Taliban
has introduced a new law which divides
Afghan society into four classes. How
many? Four classes with different
punishments prescribed for the same
crime depending on social class status
or whatever you want to call it
division. Religious scholars are placed
in the highest
Religious scholars are placed in the
highest category and are exempt from
severe punishment with admonition deemed
sufficient in case of wrongdoing.
So the highest category in Afghan
society is now religious scholars. What
do you call religious scholars in the
Indian subcontinent? I wonder. Okay.
Next. Uh the second category includes
respected elites such as tribal elders,
military commanders and influential
figures.
Second category category is mainly
warriors. Very interesting. Yeah.
Individuals from this group may be
summoned and warned but will not face
imprisonment or corporal punishment. The
third category consists of middle class
for whom imprisonment may be imposed.
And the fourth and lowest category
includes ordinary citizens who may face
imprisonment, flogging and and all that.
What is the Taliban doing?
Right?
The Taliban is an ideal society, right?
In the Islamic world, why are they
creating this four levels of society?
What would you call those four levels? I
wonder.
Anyhow, my point my point is you can
never have a society where there is zero
discrimination. Impossible.
User U7 VB V8 V says globalization
cracks backlash equals elites nervous at
WF.
Okay. Not sure if it's a question or a
statement. Um WF happened and yeah
there's unease in the west for sure.
Amisha G says, "I was reading an article
that says Russia is the world's worst
patron from Syria to Venezuela. Now Iran
Putin has overpromised and underdelled.
Do you agree?
Russia isn't powerful enough to project
power the way the US does.
What can Russia do if the Americans
decide to overthrow the government of
Venezuela? What can Russia do? Does
Russia have military base in the in the
region? Can Russia project power in the
region? Russia can't do a thing.
So if you are to make Russia your patron
then you should be aware of the
limitations of Russia.
In the case of Syria, Russia did what it
could. But at the end what happened
the see the Americans launched this this
so-called civil war in Syria, right?
Regime change operation in Syria in what
2008 910 around that time. And the
objective was to remove Bashar al-Assad
from power. And what weapons or tools
did the US use to oust Bashar al-Assad?
They used al-Qaeda and ISIS. These are
American tools. Al-Qaeda and ISIS,
terrorist groups. And what saved Syria?
Russian intervention. Russian military
intervention,
Latakia airbase and so on, right? Um
Tartus, the Russians sent military
reinforcements. The Russians sent
soldiers. They were able to project
power in Syria and they were able to
stabilize Syria and prevent a regime
change done by the US and and ISIS was
beaten back by Syria, right?
And the Russians trained Syrian troops
and you know stabilized the uh Syrian
government. But then when this Galani
comes in and uh does his move on on
Damascus, what happened? The Syrian
armed forces did not resist.
Clearly, the Americans bought some of
them. It's all about cash. So, is it
Russia that failed? No. It's I would say
Assad who failed to ensure that there
are no corrupt people in in the Syrian
armed forces.
Has Russia failed in Syria? I would
disagree. Russia did what it could. So,
Russia has limitations.
The US has more than 800 extrater
territorial military bases across the
world. The Americans can project power
anywhere. We are seeing it in real time
now, right? Russia doesn't have it. So
if you make Russia your patron, you
should be aware of Russia's limitations.
I would not say Russia is the worst
patron.
Russia tries what it can, but uh it has
limitations.
So it's your choice whether to make
Russia your patron, to make the US your
patron, or to stay entirely or to stay
remain entirely sovereign, which is the
hardest thing in the world. So it's not
like I so I I don't agree with this. I
don't agree.
So it's not like Russia has deliberately
sabotaged these nations. Russia tried
what what it could, but it was
understood that there are limitations.
In the case of Venezuela itself, when
the regime change happened, did the
Venezuelan armed forces fight back, even
attempt to fight? One guy launched a
manpad missile and he was blown to bits.
That's it. Nobody else fired a single
shot. Is that Putin's fault? No. It's
cash. Greenbacks that bought people,
right?
Kilki Susant Kiki Susan says, "I've been
reading the Art Shastra. It mentions
large chambers and buildings could be
destroyed when required to protect city
secrets of architecture. Can this be the
reason we are not able to discard much?"
I'm not sure I have read that in the
Arta Shastra
u secrets of architecture.
Look the reason we have been not been
able to discover much for example in
northern India what kind of temple
architecture did we have in northern
India why don't we why are we unaware of
this because the temples were all
brought down destroyed by Turk invaders
and occupiers only small temples remain
and whatever temples exist are all
damaged and defaced and in ruins the
destruction was done by the foreign
occupiers and invaders not by our people
right when it comes to ancient forts
like uh the old fort in Delhi etc. It
still kind of stands to some extent.
It's in terrible condition in ruins. The
ASI doesn't give a damn. It's still kind
of trying to stand. When it comes to the
fort of Kaneshka in Patiala Chandigar,
where is it? Kaneska's fort in Punjab.
Whoopsy daisy. What is this? What
happened here? One second.
Um,
Karn Nishka Fort
not super man. Fort
Akila Kila Mubarak. Q
kila.
Is this one? Kila Mubarak. Batinda.
Okay. So you have this roughly 2,000-y
old fort that still stands in Batunda,
Punjab. This fort was built by Shri
Kaneshka. Kaneshka the great still
stands. So So my point is I can give you
lots of examples like this. I am not
sure exactly what you've read. I am I
don't recall reading that the shastra.
See obviously if you have some buildings
that contain secrets and which should
not fall into the hands of invaders or
enemies makes sense to destroy them
but it's not like we randomly destroyed
temples and buildings and all that no it
was the invaders that did that and the
reason why we are not able to discover
much is because the ASI does nothing.
The archaeological survey of India is
okay.
Ripple power says, "Do cosmic voids
encode inflationary information?"
Cosmic voids, do they encode
inflationary information?
Inflationary information. So we had a
period of inflation uh in the very very
very initial moments of the universe
after the birth of the universe and the
event that we call the big bang. So
there was a period of of of super
lumininal expansion of spaceime.
Okay. Spacetime ex expanded at
mindbogling speeds that vastly ex
exceeded the speed of light. And that's
the period of time the epoch that we
call the inflationary epoch.
that began what 10 raised to minus 20
seconds into the birth of the universe
something. Yeah. Around that that sort
of thing very early universe and before
the inflationary epoch we have something
called the very early universe that
period about which we know next to
nothing.
So now we have inflation that happened
and inflation stretched everything out
and that after inflation the universe
was probably the size of a football or
something in today's terms and then it
expanded further. It's been expanding
ever since. So
what what happened during inflation?
Does some of do some of those clues
exist in cosmic void? So first of all,
what's a cosmic void? A cosmic void is
this area these areas of of space that
are essentially empty. There is
something called the boots void. Okay,
let's see the boots void. What is that?
Okay.
is void enormous nearly spherical region
of space roughly 700 million lighty
years from here and it's kind of empty
as lly as it can be it's a YouTube video
it's a brute void uh doesn't mean
there's nothing there not entirely sure
so that's the boots void and other
cosmic voids do we have any other
example cosmic voids so yeah there's
vast spaces between cosmic filaments
Okay.
Now what are these cosmic filaments?
The very largest scale in the universe.
So look coming back to the scale we have
the solar system right and moon and
planets around the sun. Then we have the
region
neighbor the stellar neighborhood which
is Proxima Centtory AB and so on so
forth Alpha Centuri all the you know
surrounding stars. Then we have the
Milky Way galaxy. Then we have the
neighboring galaxy Andromeda. And then
you have the local cluster of galaxies.
Then we have the LANA supercluster
that's a big supercluster of galaxies
and then all the superclusters are
connected together by these filaments of
dark matter and these are filaments that
we're talking about and sometimes
between between filaments we have these
cosmic voids but nothing ex essentially
the space space seem to be empty now do
these empty voids encode inflationary
information that's the question that's
being asked I'm not sure
what kind of inflationary information do
we have could we have the inflaton field
the infl we can't really detect the
inflaton field. So I'm not sure if
cosmic v voids encode inflationary
information. They are obviously
mysterious. We then they're very far
away. So we can't really say but I'm not
sure if they encode inflationary
information.
I don't I'm not aware of it. probably I
don't know would not venture a guess but
I would say
I would say I don't know that's the
answer actually okay anyway I hope I
threw some light on what cosmic voids
etc are and inflation is
Jorah TV says is it possible that
instead of simply retiring and
discarding old jets like the MIG2 we
could upgrade them into autonomous
unmanned systems and use them for uh ISR
or electronic warfare what is ISR R
reconnaissance
ISR recon
intelligence surveillance and
reconnaissance okay ISR right it's
certainly possible to do that the only
question is if you're flying um remotely
flying u
um a MIG2 or if you have an AI on board
that flies it autonomously the only
issue with the MIG2 is how reliable is
it is the air are the air airframes and
the engines and so on because the big
21s have had so many crashes and
failures and if you're flying an
autonomous big 21 what if it fails and
and then uh you know crashes and causes
fatalities that's the only thing
um it certainly is is possible it's
feasible you would need a high quality
AI system uh that's that's taught the
rules right what to do and so on the
other thing is that if you want to use
it for ISR intelligence surveillance
reconnaissance the MIG21 is a massive
thing, right? It's a massive thing. It's
a It's a big unit. For ISR, you would
ideally want to use smaller assets.
No, a drone that this that is this size
almost undetectable.
Fly it high and have it loiter for 10
hours and do ISR quietly. A MIG 21 is
big, visible, shows up on radar,
massive, loud, etc.
makes way more sense to use drones,
but you could use the MIG 21s as decoys,
autonomous decoys or or wingmen. You
know, you could either fly them remotely
or autonomously. Have have them have an
AI fly them autonomously and use them
for, you know, first strike penetration
or whatever to absorb the initial fire
or whatever. That sort of thing you
could do. So I'm sure we can find good
uses for MIG 21s, but I'm not sure if
they are the right platform for ISR
work. Electronic warfare. I suppose we
could find uh ways of using the MIG 21
for electronic warfare also. You know,
pit them with jammer pods or something
and uh send them in first before you
send in man fighters. That sort of thing
can be done. So I'm sure there are
creative ways of of repurposing the MIG2
um in beneficial ways in advantageous
ways but I'm not sure if they they are
good uh platforms for ISR work for other
work. Yeah, sure indeed.
Fast snail says big reason for dirty
public places is good stains. Why is it
prevalent only in India? What can the
government do? In the west we don't see
it. People smoke or vape.
Yeah. Every every culture has its own
weird things right now. When it comes to
good casta stains and you eat eating
chewing beetlenut and all that I'll tell
you what. Okay. PG beetle nut
papua nu guini okay
in papwa nu guini also you have this
practice of chewing beetle nuts and
spitting them out and all that. So it's
it's not like it's only limited to India
but it's a pretty nasty practice you
know. Uh the gutka is something else.
It's not exactly bettnut but it's part
of the of this practice of chewing
things and splitting them out.
uh beetlen nuts are used in eating pan
right and there are various kinds of pan
sweet pan and tobacco pan and what not
else pan whatever and then the gutka is
this little ghastly little sachets that
people I suppose they contain tobacco
and god knows what else and people chew
that and spit that out and gives them
those ghastly red teeth or whatever or
brown whatever right and obviously I
completely agree that it's a terrible
practice and people who do that they
have this habit of spitting around right
spitting in some public corner some
public place and that that that
obviously is is is horrible to see those
places with those gutka spit stains.
Um in western countries people don't
have this uh this habit this practice
it's it's unknown to them. People there
typically I suppose smoke cigarettes or
or vape these days those chemical
pouches or whatever.
Um
yeah people yeah in the west it's not
there that's for the west seems cleaner
is cleaner is cleaner so what can the
government of India do about good cara
I suppose you ban good cara right the
thing is the thing is that
I suppose in a in a large population you
there is I mean you you should allow
people to have some vices right it's not
like you should encourage bad habits but
You recognize the fact that in society a
certain number of people will do certain
will indulge in certain bad habits.
That's why alcohol is not banned.
Cigarettes are not banned. Tobacco is
not banned. I suppose I suppose in India
maybe a large number of people do this
good car thing. Looks like that. Uh and
if you ban that maybe you lose votes if
you ban that people get dissatisfied. Um
so what the government does is is it
taxes these things. Uh and I suppose
tobacco products and good car products
are taxed higher percentages than other
things. Sin tax they call it or
whatever. Even I suppose even alcohol.
Um
what can the government do? Well, I
would I would say the government should
ban this. This is a terrible practice.
Terrible. It's bad for your health. It's
bad for your teeth. It's bad for uh for
for for public cleanliness and all that.
Right. It it makes the makes the country
look dirty.
Ideally, you should ban it, but then you
should also ban tobacco, I suppose.
And um well, that'll make a lot of
people, I suppose, unhappy.
Um
so what could can you you know
realistically do? Realistically, what
you can do is you can ban spitting. If
somebody's caught spitting, they should
be fined a large sum of money. And to
make this happen, you need proper
enforcement. In India we have laws we
have zero enforcement at times in some
places especially when it comes to these
little things littering and spitting and
all that
people are never punished for these
things even for uh violating traffic
rules traffic laws who punished ever
once in a while you're punished but you
can get away with a lot of things in
India because of lacks enforcement so
what India needs is proper laws and and
strict enforcement harsh enforcement
then things will
Sergeant Skylin says, "Can something
good come from this Trump term? A lot of
good will come for the US.
Are you talking about something good for
the rest of the world?" Well,
look, Trump works for his country, of
course. Right? Every leader is supposed
to work for their country, hopefully in
mutually beneficial ways with other
countries. So, a lot of good will come
for the US, right? the US gets more
powerful. The US throws around its power
everywhere. Consolidates its Western
Hemisphere uh dominance
um gets more nations in line.
Potentially acquires Greenland and so
much more. All that is good for the US,
good for India. Why will Trump do
something that's good for India? Why
will Trump do something that's good for
China? Trump and the US don't want to
see India grow and rise.
So why will they do some anything good
for India? They'll pressurize India.
They'll pressurize China. They'll
pressurize Russia. So whatever good
comes out of the Trump term, that good
will be good for the US, not for the
rest of the world. Especially not for
India, Russia or China. That's just the
way it is.
Hyphen says, "Does nuclear deterrence
still work in a world of cyber warfare
and hypersonic weapons? Also, what can
India do to stay sovereign and keep
growing?" Okay, two questions. Does
nuclear deterrence still work in a world
of cyber warfare? And absolutely it
does. It does. It is madness to launch a
nuclear weapon even with hypersonics or
whatever.
Right? You can succeed in nuclear war
only if you launch a massive massive
first strike that is undetected
and and if it is a decapitation strike.
And in today's world with all the
surveillance, all the everything, it's
impossible to launch a nuclear strike
that goes undetected.
You have massive networks of satellites
all across Earth orbit. You have swads
of ground stations everywhere whose only
job is to detect nuclear launches or or
missile launches. Right? So the moment
you see a missile that's launched with
a parabolic ballistic trajectory or a
near ballistic trajectory or if you see
a missile that has long range
capabilities that is being launched and
so you know what are the characteristics
of a potential nuclear launch. So
so you're going to have a response then
and that is devastating. It's it's
mutually assured destruction. So nuclear
deterrence does still work. It does
still work. Of course, one can some some
actors may gamble, you know, do do a
tactical strike or low threshold, low,
you know, low low yield strike, maybe 20
kiloton strike or something, you know,
on a battlefield, that sort of thing.
Will that can you get away with that?
That sort of thing. I mean, there are
all these theories about that, but at
the end of the day, a nuclear strike is
a nuclear strike and it's going to
invite a response. I think a nuclear
deterrence still does work.
It does work. Cyber warfare,
hypersonics, doesn't matter. It it still
works. Uh what can India do to stay
sovereign and keep growing? First of
all, avoid any major conflict. If
there's a major conflict, finish it in 3
to 7 days maximum, right? Um bolster
your military strength.
India needs to bolster its military
might. India needs to stockpile tens of
thousands of missiles first of all of
various kinds including ICBMs.
Okay, India needs to do that. India
needs a stockpile of tens of thousands
of missiles. India needs a massive
stockpile of ammunition.
Okay, India needs to stay a breast of uh
the latest advances advances in warfare
which primarily we see the as lessons of
the Ukraine war, right? Uh various kinds
of drones, autonomous systems, loitering
munitions, kamicaz drones, all of that.
India I believe has reasonably good
cyber warfare offensive defensive
capabilities. India needs to develop a
massive navy. India needs to get going
on submarines
and also you know the air force part of
things. Of course if you have high
quality missiles you don't really need a
very that can compensate for any
shortfall in terms of fighter jets and
all that.
uh and of course along with this India
needs to keep growing as an economy you
know at least 6 7 8% at least 6% per
year uh GDP growth wise and India is
doing the right things by by signing
FTAs potentially with the European Union
and other countries you know excellent
work on this front excellent work and at
the end of the day India will need
political continuity political stability
and high quality leadership and India
will need reforms internal reforms
India needs massive internal reforms,
ease of doing business, education, all
of those things. Education is like
completely neglected. But education, the
quality of education determines the
quality of your people. So all these
things need to be done in the next 20
years.
Okay.
Vijay Viki says, why is ISO
failing to put strategic satellites in
space? Possible sabotage. only strategic
satellites are failing in the recent
past and even for Navik satellites
unfunctional now.
What's the what could be the cause of
this? Well, let's think of the
scenarios.
See the PSLV which is used to launch
these satellites, it had 21 consecutive
successful launches. It had become so
successful that a PSLV launch was
boring. That is the ultimate accolade
you can pay that your launches are
boring because we know they are so
successful. There's no excitement is we
know it's going to work. That's how
successful the PSV was. And now we have
two consecutive failures. Each time the
third stage something goes wrong. Each
time when you have a strategic military
satellite, right? And apparently with
the Navic satellites
um let's see about Navic. What's the
status? Uh how many Navic satellites?
uh does India have in orbit? How many?
Eight operational satellites blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah etc. Uh what is
the state the status the ah
status ah
the status
of India's
8 navic satellites
uh how many of these are operational
critical near defunct status only four
of the 11 launch satellites are
providing core reliable navigation
services according According to Vion and
Reddit users, I'm not sure how reliable
these things are but whatever. Atomic
clock failures. Uh the atomic clocks
obviously we are purchasing from the
west and those have failed. So only four
satellites are fully operational which
is a disaster.
Okay. Five older satellites are
completely defunct.
Uh
and the first nextG satellite NVS01 is
operational but NVS02 failed to launch
to reach its target orbit. What is this
NVS02 satellite 29 Jan?
Okay.
What happened? 29th Jan. What happened
to it? Was it launched? Launch fuel
system failure.
It was launched on GSLV F-15
29th January. And this failed.
This failed. So even the GSLV is
suffering problems.
That's where we are. That's pretty bad
situation. So, is failing somehow or is
there sabotage? Now some of you may
remember a year or two ago I had put out
this video analysis
in which I said that there is a strong
possibility that the Chundrean 2
uh spacecraft was sabotaged
and there were this analysis faced a lot
of criticism
from various experts and today we have
this happening two consecutive PSLV
launches have failed our Navic system is
essentially
Only four out of 11 satellites are
operational. One of the Navic satellites
was launched on GSLV that did not reach
orbit. Looks like critical systems,
critical satellites
that push the envelope
are being targeted. I think there is a
very high possibility
there is sabotage. Maybe
spies inside the system. Maybe moles in
the inside the system. Maybe some kind
of
some kind of
some way of potentially hacking
or sabotaging the launches, the vehicles
or something from outside. Most likely
not from outside. Most likely internal
sabotage. Looks like that's a very
strong possibility. I'm not claiming
it's 100% certain that there is internal
sabotage of some kind. I'm saying there
is there seems like it it
From a logical perspective, I think it's
highly possible.
From a logical perspective, it's there's
a high probability that there is
sabotage that's going on.
And India needs to get it act get its
act together. Whatever sabotage may or
may not be happening, look into it. If
it is indeed sabotage, hypothetically,
identify the source of the sabotage. Um,
apprehend
the whatever people may possibly be be
involved in this, right?
So, yeah, this is this is a very serious
situation
and uh yeah, very concerning for sure.
Very concerning.
What's also concerning is that ISRO is
launching like five rockets a year.
Five rockets a year. SpaceX is is is
launching like five rockets a week.
And ISRO is launching five rockets a
year. Is it Israel's fault? No, it's the
it's the government's fault. The
government seems to have zero ambitions
now in India for India in space.
I don't know what's going on. Seriously,
baffling. Absolutely baffling.
It's like ISRO is no longer in the
space. We've given up on space. Who
cares? Who cares? Doesn't matter, right?
Crazy madness.
Keshov says if the US seeks a land
border to base its military
infrastructure and power and project
power against China, why haven't they
gone after Bhutan too high?
What
a land border to base military
infrastructure and project power against
China. If the US puts things in Bhutan,
China will take over Bhutan the next
day.
I mean it's we are not in kindergarten
here, right?
It has to be feasible.
If the US puts personnel or equipment or
weapons, military infrastructure in
Bhutan, China will invade the next
morning and take over Bhutan.
And why will Bhutan allow this to
happen?
Why you think Bhutan's available to
whoever wants to do whatever whatever
stuff? Bhutan seeks to continue
existing.
Bhutan knows China is its biggest
threat. Bhutan knows that India is the
only nation that can save Bhutan and
continue Bhutan's existence.
Why will Bhutan invite retaliation from
China by doing something so stupid? If
the Chinese invade Bhutan, do you think
the Americans can save Bhutan?
I mean, think logically.
Think beyond the surface level. What
happens if you if if the US does this?
What happens if Bhutan is so stupid it
allows Americans to put some weapons in
Bhutan and some personnel? What happens
next?
What will China's response be?
Have you thought of that? And if China
invades, let's say, then what will the
Americans be able to do?
Do does America have a land border with
Bhutan so that it can do something? Can
America project power in the Bhutan
region?
Will India allow Bhutan to allow the
Americans to put weapons there or
whatever there? I mean, think of it.
Think of it. Let's think seriously here,
right?
Okay. Raza Ali Shirazi says, "Greeting
from the land of Nadesha." You all
remember him. Nadesha was a one real son
of a wasn't he? Nadesha.
High quality bastard. Was he? He was
Nadasha.
Okay. Ammon Kumar Dankar says
reminder Mr. Bramud best time for Mr.
Ramdei also. All right sir. Thank you
for the reminders. Thank you.
Chira Shinat says hi Kushal.
I think this is not for me.
Who's Kushell? This is not Kushell.
I am pretty sure this is you have put
this question on the wrong channel. I
think you are looking for Kushel. A uh
not me.
Would you like me to take this question
because this is not for me. Let's take
it anyway. My name is Abhijit. Abijit.
By the way, Abijit, not Kushell. I
appeared on Koshal's channel few days
ago. This is Abijit here. Okay.
How can No. Can India become rich within
its current framework? Most countries
industrialized under strong strong state
control and democratized later in the
'90s. Is India doing trying to do too
much at once? India is trying India you
are absolutely right take the example of
South Korea for example South Korea
industrialized under strong state
control democratized only later South
Korea used to be a dictatorship
only after it properly industrialized
did it become supposedly a democracy
under US occupation of course but still
on paper a democracy
um and there are plenty of such examples
right India
has never
had that strong state control that can
properly industrialize it. India is this
chaotic democracy, isn't it? When you
have states that have at times more
power than the center, states, the
states can veto the center. If the
center wants to, let's say, you know,
open up some industries in a certain
state, they can say, "No, no, our
farmers protest. our our our
under the protest and we we will not
allow this to happen. We want to remain
dirt poor. We don't want industries here
and it works and then other states will
say okay bring it here we'll benefit.
This sort of system doesn't work.
India will have to significantly reform
things if India wants to be rich and
powerful. The current framework is
loaded against India. It's like
it's like the system is rigged against
India. The system wants to ensure that
India doesn't succeed. System is
designed
to keep India mediocre and poor.
Yeah. So India is not trying to do too
much at once. India is trying to do
everything within the confines and
boundaries and constraints of the worst
system imaginable.
So you are right. It doesn't it can't
work and that's what that's why India
needs reforms. massive reforms which I
keep saying.
Chira Shrinat says can India become rich
within its current chaotic framework?
Most countries industrialized under a
strong state control in the 50s and 60s.
Uh yeah, I just answered this question.
It is very hard for India to become rich
and powerful within the current chaotic
framework. I agree with you. It's it's
very hard things have to change.
Okay. Naven says the dome of Imam Ali
Shin Iraq and the open curved arches and
Ians of Montas Syria Madarasa Iraq
remember resemble similar architecture
of Taj Mahal and both of them built
centuries before Taj Mahal. Thank you
very much for the very interesting
observation.
Chance says, "Uh, Western folks on X
often make fun of Indians saying they
are the true Arians with pics of Indians
with dominant AASI features underneath.
What's the apt report to make to this to
make them shut?" The apt report is to
either mute them or block them and move
on with your life.
Who cares what they say?
Who cares what they say? How How does it
Why do you need
external validation?
Why? Let them say I mean you walking on
a street and dogs bark at you. You're
going to bother the you're going to go
after the dogs are you you're going to
move on with life, right? How do we care
what they say?
You can't fight them all.
So my my point I mean it's not like I
don't see this. I just move on. But if
you want to I mean look it's very easy
to to sell a lie
an oversimplification of things when
the response is complicated.
So if you want to respond to these
folks, okay, then you have to explain
the details. You to explain that this
Arian invasion/migration theory is a
myth. You to explain that it was cooked
up by Max Mueller with the u five what
4,000
4,000 year um creation story of Jesus
Christ and God Yahweh and all that in
mind.
So he put an arbitrary date of 1500 BC
for the Iranian invasion which has no
basis in anything any any any any
concrete truth. Then you have to show
how all the claims of the iron invasion
theory are false which is why they had
to create Arian migration theory. And
then you have to show how the facts of
the Arian migration theory are also
false. Then you have to show that India
has tremendous genet genetic diversity
the second highest genetic diversity
outside of Africa which is why you have
people of so many different kinds of
facial features and so on so on. So you
have to write a long essay to counter
one picture, one meme. Do you have the
time to do all this?
Right? These people seek to waste your
time and energy. I would say just move
on. Ignore such people. Block them or
mute them or ignore them. That's it.
Shirakes says, "I was curious if you
have paused your podcasts as I haven't
seen any recent episodes. if you plan to
restart them. It would be great to have
Abija Aritra and Ram Di back on the
show. I have kind of you know I've not
entirely stopped the podcasts. I have
kind of uh reduced the frequency.
I've done more than 100 now and I've
learned a lot lot of lessons along the
way. So there are some really really
great guests that I've had. One of them
is Abijah Aditra obviously um Dr. to me
actually Jane and I'm I'm sure I can
name a few more great guests who are
outstanding when who I would have who
and whom I would love to have on my show
on my on the podcast again but I've also
realized that a lot of the times
many times I've realized during the
conversations that I'm not sure why I
call this person because I kind of know
more than them
so that's why I have decided to now
bring the frequency of the podcast
episodes down. It's not going to be it
used to be like once a week or twice a
week earlier. I think once a week at
least. Right now it's going to be once
in whenever I feel like only when I
happen to speak to somebody really
interesting who really has something
really valuable to contribute that I
can't contribute. Right? So it's going
to be it's going to be there once in a
while. Once in a while uh but yeah so
that's the status right now. It's not
stopped. It's not paused. It's kind of a
little infrequent right now and that's
that's where we are.
Munabaya says IG V JPY Modi who played
better geopolitics against US and China?
Uh IG Indra Gandhi V. What's a V? Who's
a V? VJP Baj Pai. Baj Pai Modi. Who
played better geopolitics against us and
China?
Indra Gandhi well she did a great thing
by by bifurcating Pakistan resecting
Pakistan
that's that's one of the greatest
military achievements since 1947
so full marks for that waji well without
wajpay
we would not have a nuclear deterrent
today so he showed spine of steel in
going ahead with the nuclear um tests in
Mrs. Gandhi also had conducted a nuclear
test in 194 1974 but then she for
whatever reason sheld the nuclear
program Mr. Waji reactivated it and then
converted that into an act actual active
nuclear deterrent right and Mr. Modi has
taken Indian foreign policy to the next
level obviously right over the years
over the past 11 12 years he has totally
sidelined Pakistan shown a very hard
stance against Pakistan the kind of
stance no other leader has done in the
past and he has expanded India's economy
sign significantly
had this multi-aligned
foreign policy that has worked very well
for India so I would say all of these
leaders all three of these leaders have
done a lot of great good a lot of great
at least some good and some great but
overall I would say that of all the
Indian prime ministers I am aware of
that we've had since 47 overall
cumulatively Mr. Modi has been the most
successful in terms of foreign policy uh
geopolitics etc. Yeah,
Vive Singh says, "Non UNSC, UN Security
Council, non UN Security Council nations
are joining the board of peace. Is it
going to be a competitor of the UN or
will it fade away like the League of
Nations? Do you see a EU US conflict
soon?"
So, Donald J. Trump, American president,
47th president, he has uh
instituted
constituted this this board of peace
thing and there's a bunch of nations in
the board of peace.
So what does this tell us? Is this going
to be a competitor to the United Nations
or is it going to fade out? Look, one
thing it tells us is that the United
Nations is failing as a global
institution. It's not able to guarantee
the peace in any any region. The UN is
able to do nothing when it comes to
Gaza. What was the UN able to do?
nothing. The UN is a failure. The UN is
increasingly irrelevant, almost
completely irrelevant. So Trump
constituting a border of peace that will
actually guarantee the peace in Gaza, it
is a slap in the face of the UN. It it
shows the world the UN is irrelevant. So
that much is definitely established and
that is definitely something that Trump
has already achieved through this board
of peace. Now
if you look at the kind of nations that
have joined the board of peace, you have
nations like Turkey and Pakistan
which doesn't give a lot of credibility
to the board of peace. Pakistan a
terrorist regime.
Turkey enabler of terrorism, supporter
of ISIS. You have such nations in the
board of peace. These are all
opportunists
who seek to curry favor with Donald J.
Trump and achieve something for
themselves.
and Shabb Sharif is it's and aim it's
not like they're doing something for
Pakistan they're doing it for their own
benefit dictators tinpot dictator well
Shabb Sharif is the puppet essentially
he's aim's puppet he's the standin for
Munir so um that's the board of peace
and if you want to be a permanent member
you have to pay a billion dollars and
then and even then Trump is the lifelong
chairman of the board of peace that sort
of thing so it's kind of a circus to
some extent
So uh will the board of peace last? I
it it it can last only if it has global
recognition. If it it can last only if
it has recognition from nations like
India, Russia, China,
right? Only then will it be legitimate
if outside of the US the three biggest
economies stay out or the three most
powerful nations not biggest economies
three most powerful nations outside the
apart from the US stay out then it
doesn't get any real legitimacy so I
expect that if India Russia China don't
join then this thing will eventually
fade out do I see a EU Russ US conflict
soon I don't not not a war there's
obviously tensions and so or so on, but
not of war, not a not a military
conflict.
Hyphen 6552 says, "Sorry for multiple
questions, but will climate change
become a p primary driver of conflict?"
No, that's that's the first answer. No,
it won't. Or a threat multiplier. It
could potentially multiply threats if
there is massive effects of climate
change like floods or massive u you know
um you know natural disasters. Also, are
human rights promoted for moral reasons
or as tool of tools of leverage? Okay.
About climate change, it won't be a
primary driver of conflict, but it could
be a threat multiplier in some some
geographies. For example, it can be a
threat multiplier in a geography that is
for example uh prone to regular
earthquakes. It obviously is is
something that you have to uh mitigate
or or consider as part of your
lifestyle. If there's a contract there,
it obviously is going to have effects.
Let's say you have a region that's prone
to volcanism, the ring of fire region.
Well, there you're going to have issues,
right? Um
it can be a major driver for a threat
multiplier for low-lying countries in
the ocean, oceanic countries like
Maldives. If the ocean levels do rise,
we we don't see that happening, but if
they do rise, then it's going to be a
threat. It could be a threat for
Bangladesh and then it could drive
conflict. If the ocean levels rise like
say 3 4 meters in the next 20 30 years
if that happens but um that is well if
that happens that sort of thing. So it
depends on the geography on the country
on the local uh politics and so much
more. Now are human rights promoted for
moral reasons or as tools of leverage?
Well, human rights ideally should be
promoted for moral reasons because human
rights are should be sacrosant wherever
you have uh wherever you have human
beings. But uh if you look at the
champions of human rights like the
United States, they use human rights as
a tool of leverage. They use human
rights as a stick to beat certain
nations with. So they will so when it
comes to let's say the US attempting
regime change in Syria well they
supported ISIS and al-Qaeda
or the moderate re rebels al-Qaeda are
the moderate rebels ISIS are nasty but
they will they will turn the other way
while they do this stuff that sort of
thing and today you have an ISIS
terrorist who is the so-called president
of Syria and he meets with Donald Trump
what happened to your human rights
But when it comes to other countries,
they will use uh so-called human rights
uh challenges or whatever based on
whatever reports they put out as a stick
to beat the country with. So it's it's
all tools of leverage.
People power says, "Is interior
reconstructible from boundary data?"
You're talking about the holographic
principle, are you?
I mean, I'm I'm sure you're talking
about physics here, aren't you?
boundary data. Let's talk about
let's talk about black holes for
example. Okay. So if you have a an
uncharged non-rotating black hole,
it's called a Schwarz chilled black
hole. Okay. And it's it's the the
solution to the Einstein field equations
is a perfectly spherically symmetric
solution. So it's a spherical black
hole. It's not rotating. It doesn't have
angular momentum. And let's say it has
no charge. Typically black holes have
very little charge. if if any at all.
But okay. So then you have a spherical
object
which seems to contain at the center
it's at its heart a singularity
and the singularity is a probably
mathematical artifact but it's not a
coordinate artifact. It's an actual
physical singularity from the equations
which means the equations break down to
the center. You have a region of
infinite curvature infinite density
which is unphysical. It's division by
zero which actually indicates that
there's something somewhat wrong with
the equations. It needs an improvement
of some kind which means it's physics
that we don't understand there. U now at
the surface the surface what is the
surface of a black hole. So when you are
falling into a black hole do you see
some kind of signboard? Here here is the
point of no return you don't see
anything. The surface is is an imaginary
surface. It's called the event horizon.
Okay.
And you can construct this boundary at
the event horizon.
And there
so the holographic principle says that
this this two-dimensional surface uh it
encodes
all the information that's inside the
black hole in some scrambled encrypted
form or whatever. Uh that's the
holographic principle. But can you
reconstruct the interior from the
boundary data? I'm not sure we can. I
don't think we can. I mean I would like
to know what's at the heart of the black
hole. What what does the singularity
look like? Does do we actually have a
singularity? So the boundary data
doesn't really tell us anything about
the singularity.
Whatever we know of the interior of of a
black hole is from the solutions of the
Einstein field equations.
Um
the the holographic data the the the
surface boundary information. So one
thing we know is that uh the surface
area
of the boundary of the of the event
horizon it is
proportional to the entropy of the black
hole. The amount of let's say disorder
in the black hole. Okay that's one thing
we know that's black hole
thermodynamics. But can we
can we determine whatever is inside the
black hole? How many photons went in?
How many how many neutrinos went in? How
many charged particles, atoms, whatever
went in? Can we do that from the
boundary data? We can't. We can't. At
this point in time, we can't. Okay. Dian
plane crash says, "Your opinion on
Soviet icranoplanes.
Soviet erranoplanes were this gigantic
whoreboards."
What's a horcraft? Horcrafts. So, what's
a horrorcraft first of all? So a
horsecraft is this uh
essentially it's a floating vehicle that
floats on a cushion of air and it has
these propellers which propel it
forward. So it's this uh vehicle that
that you can drive over land or even
sea. You can drive it across a river.
It'll be it will it will be floating on
a cushion of air and you can just drive
it over a river. You can drive it across
over a sea. And these echrano plans were
gigantic
warcrafts and those could carry dozens
of troops, maybe hundreds of troops,
maybe even vehicles, very large. Um, so
let's see what these looked like. First
of all, what's what does the horcraft
look like?
Socraft, it looks like this. Okay, we
have horcraft services in various parts
of India. This is a small one. This is a
medium-sized hovercraft. As you can see,
it's it's go it's it's traveling over a
river or or or water. This one is on
land.
So, typically you use it to cross to
essentially travel over or over water.
Now, what does an echranoplan look like?
So, it was this gigantic horcraft beast.
Okay, you could use it to launch
invasions.
You can see how many engines it had.
Eight engines. And I suppose these were
heavily armed too. You can see these
missile tubes or whatever. Right. This
is another uh the Caspian Sea monster.
Massive massive beastly object. So you
had these
plants. I'm not sure how many were
built. I'm sure I'm pretty sure not very
many were built. This is Darpa. Okay,
forget about Darpa. So these were
massive designs. I don't remember what
the strategic or tactical use of these
was and a few of these were built but uh
these were eventually abandoned and they
are no longer in u operation.
The Chinese have plan like like like
like vehicles warcrafts that can
potentially be used for an invasion of
Taiwan. Okay, that sort of thing. Uh so
that's what I know about econoplants.
Very interesting.
a vehicle, military vehicle that that
the Soviets built. Uh I'm sure it's it's
a good concept and can still be adapted
for 21st century warfare, especially for
amphibious invasions and expeditionary
warfare.
Okay.
Okay. So if for example if India wants
to practice an invasion
of some country some hypothetical
country then you could take off from
let's say Vishakapatnam or whatever on
an Eranoplan like vehicle and practice
an invasion of the Anderman islands you
know just for practice purpose and are
anyway ours but you practice so you
could do that if you had econom like
vehicles maybe each plant could
potentially carry let's 100 troops or
200 troops. Launch 10 of these and you
have a pretty good invasion force. No
marines that sort of thing.
Shivanch says, "Have you read Mr.
Ambedkar? Do you subscribe to any of his
ideas?" I unfortunately have not read
any of Dr. Ambedkar. So I am not aware
of his ideas. Right. There are so many
historical figures, you know,
fascinating historical figures, very
important historical figures. So many of
these in past history. So many of these
that it's impossible to study each of
them. uh and I have never had the
opportunity or the time or somehow it's
never happened that I uh got the chance
to read about Dr.
So I am not aware of his ideas in in any
any great detail.
Caitana on tech says since inception has
the US always interfered in other
count's affairs? When did this start?
Well the US so the first of all the what
was the inception of the US? The
inception of the United States was
Europeans interfering in the internal
affairs of the Americas.
See Columbus set out from Spain in the
hope of discovering India and he
stumbled into the Caribbean region and
he thought this was India. I discovered
India. He goes back to Spain and says I
found the Indies. I found India and so
on. Eventually the Spanish realize this
is not India. It's a new land that they
found. Eventually they find La Florida
the flowered coast which is now Florida.
And then eventually uh it's the English
who first resort to piracy and then they
they actually go and uh set settle down.
You first have Jamestown which the
Americans don't want to talk about
because it was a disaster, nasty
disaster. And then you have Plymouth in
what is now the Massachusetts region.
And then they invade
this land and massacre the natives,
genocide the natives and set up
eventually the United States.
It was first British colonies and then
1776 you have the formation of the
United States.
So this was the formation of the US. The
creation of the US was was was the theft
of land
from the natives and the decimation
genocide of the natives. And then you
have further westward expansion at the
cost of the lives and territories of the
natives.
But this was interference in the
internal affairs of the native people of
the Americas who hardly exist at all
anymore. And and then they stole
territory from Mexico in the 19th
century. What 40 1848 was it? US Mexico
war. When did it happen? Let's quickly
take a look. Okay. US Mexico war
46. Okay. I was off by two years. It it
ended in 48. So how how do you have
territories in the US that are called
Colorado, Teas, California? Those are
Spanish names, right? These were all
Mexican territories which was Mexico was
once called New Spain.
And then in what 1823, the Americans
instituted this foreign policy called
the Monroe Doctrine that we won't allow
any European power to interfere in the
Americas anymore.
that was obviously interference in the
internal affairs of other South American
nations, Central American nations
and so on. So it's always been that sort
of thing. See the America the United
States was founded by invaders and
occupiers. European invaders and
occupiers. And what was in their blood?
Invasion and occupation and plunder and
pillage and theft. That's how Australia
was created. Australia was once
populated only by native people, the
so-called Aboriginal people. Where are
they today? What happened to the natives
of Tasmania?
Not a single one is alive today. This is
what the the the Anglo-Saxons have done
across the world. Interference in other
countries affairs, theft of countries,
theft of land, genocide, plunder,
pillage. What did they do in India? The
same Anglo-Saxons.
They um artificially engineered hundreds
of famines
and killed hundreds of millions of
Indians. Your textbooks won't teach you
this.
So when I say this, people will question
me. What are you talking about? You've
gone crazy. Your textbooks won't teach
you this. Your NCERT revisions, do they
teach you how many artificial famines
the British engineered? How did they
engineer the famines step by step?
And how many Indians were killed as a as
a consequence? They won't teach you
this. This is the problem.
Okay. Shahon says, "Is Ali Adris really
that great?" I'm sorry. Who Who is
Alris? Let's see who is Alidris.
Muhammad Ali.
Uh I haven't studied the life and the
story of Muhammad Ali.
Uh Abu Abdullah Muhammad Ali Kuri
Alassani
what
was an Arabic Muslim geographer and
ctographer who served in the court of
King Roger II at Palmo Sicily. He was
born in Suta belonging to the Alam
Muravit dynasty. Okay, I am not aware of
this fine gentleman so I don't know.
Sorry.
Right. Next. Giora TV says, "Isn't it a
good idea that to fix India's language
dispute in the future? All major
regional languages should be taught in
schools. Aren't so many years enough for
kids to learn a few languages?" So, see,
it's it's I would say it's a on paper a
good idea, but think of it practically.
Let's say you're a kid in in in some
state in India. Let's say you are a kid
in in Andhra Pradesh.
So typically what a kid goes through in
school is that you have to learn the
native language as one of the subjects.
Then you have to learn Hindi as the
nation language. That's the second one.
And if you're in the English medium, you
have to learn English the third
language. So out of your seven or eight
subjects, three are languages.
And you learn this year after year.
first standard, second, third, blah,
blah, blah. 1000 all the way I suppose
to 12th standard. 12 years of your life,
you're learning three languages when you
could have spent that time learning
something way more interesting if you
only had to learn one language.
So if you make kids learn five
languages, six languages, what else will
they have time for to learn?
That's the problem.
That's the problem. You should have one.
See in my opinion you should be taught
two languages. One is your native lang
your your mother tongue.
Your education should be in your mother
tongue not in a foreign language.
And apart from your mother tongue you
should be taught one national or
civilizational language which in my
opinion should be Sanskrit.
And there should be no foreign language
taught to any kid. If they want to learn
some foreign language whether it is
French, whether it is German, whether
it's Chinese, Japanese, Swahili,
whatever, let them learn in their own
free time as a hobby. No one's
preventing you from stopping you from
learning a foreign language. But in the
Indian education system, you should be
taught instructed in the mother tongue
and you should be taught the
civilizational language Sanskrit. That's
it.
So if you are a school, if you're a kid
from Karnataka, your education should be
in the Canada language and you should be
taught one language apart from that
which is Sanskrit. If you are from
Assam, you should be taught in the Assam
is language. All your education and
apart from that you should be taught
Sanskrit. That way that way everybody
has one language that everyone can
communicate in which is the
civilizational language and you are also
being instructed in the bad tongue which
makes your education so much easier.
That's what should be done.
Teaching 500 different languages will
it's it's pointless. It's pointless. Our
civilization always had this issue that
we have so many languages. We are a
genuine civilization. We are like a
continent in our own own right. Hundreds
of languages spoken around and thousands
of thousands of dialects. So how did we
solve the problem? by having a single
civilizational language that everybody
understood everywhere or at least the
educated people, highly educated people
understood everywhere. So you could
travel across the country and no matter
what language people spoke, you could
communicate. That's what needs to happen
instead of having all kinds of languages
taught. That that's my opinion. You can
feel free to disagree with that.
Rahul Ladu says which tech should India
gain very urgently? India should um
which tech
first of all India should develop its
own large language models and AI systems
indigenous trained on indigenous
sovereign data.
It's I have no issue with us scraping
the entire world's internet and getting
the data but it should be trained on our
terms.
That's what needs to happen. So we need
to have our own lang large large
language models, our own AI systems. See
and not necessarily large language
models. Some should be LLMs. Some should
be trained on something else. You know
you have data apart from text data,
right? You have video data. You have got
audiovisisual data. Train your AI models
on all kinds of data not just text which
is LLMs. That's one thing that's
urgently required in India because we
are not even of we are not even
participating in the AI race as of now.
We're not
right. Uh you may have significant AI
penetration in India but that doesn't
mean we are a leading AI nation. We are
not a leader. We are not even second
rank. We not even in the second
category. We're nowhere right now. I
hope some work is being done and let's
see the results first instead of
boosting. Uh that's one thing India
needs to do. What other technologies? Um
jet engine technology
obviously that needs to happen rapidly.
Um what else?
Materials science.
Um miniaturization of nuclear uh nuclear
reactors for submarines and so on. Um
India is behind in many technologies. We
should catch up with all of these
urgently urgently. India needs to also
become a major player in the space race.
So what technology is needed for that?
Heavy lift rockets. We currently have
light light lift rockets. Our most
powerful rocket the GSL can lift 4,000
kilograms to uh to geocynchronous orbits
which is which is a respectable amount
but compared to the big players it's
okay. So a lot of these things need to
happen.
Uh, Pratam Sony says, "Five rules of
power in and its nature for nation and
individual.
Five rules of power."
Ah, it's been a while since I've thought
about the rules of power. Power,
how do I explain power?
Power is is is like a force. Okay?
Power, I don't know about five rules of
power, okay? But, uh, power is is
What is power? First of all, do we even
know what power is? Instead of giving
you five rules of power, let me explain
what power actually is. So, one easy
metaphor I can give you is this. Let's
say I have a million followers on social
media. H
let's say I have a million followers
across social media. That means that
about a million people
will sometimes
pay attention to me and sometimes take
some of what I say seriously. Sometimes
it means that I have some influence over
these people. I may not have full
influence over all of them but some of
them find me interesting or whatever
that's why they follow me and sometimes
they'll take me seriously at least some
of what I say seriously. That is
influence. That is not power. But let's
say I have a million guys.
Let's say I have a million people who
are highly trained, highly heavily armed
and who will obey me without question.
That is power. Huge difference between
power and influence. So the power, what
is the meaning of power? The power is
power is the ability
to compel outcomes
whether someone likes or not. That's
power. and then you can figure out what
are the rules of power based on that. So
that's what I will tell you at this
point in time.
Fast snail says what if China proposes
to send troops to help Russia just like
North Korea did
so they are battle battle tested would
Russia welcome it? Would see a red flag?
That's an interesting hypothetical
scenario.
So
let's say China has decided for whatever
reason we'll send troops to help Russia
just like North Korea did and we want
our troops to be battle tested and
Russia gets additional troops who who
will fight on its behalf. Would Russia
welcome it? Would see a red flag? I
think Russia would be very cautious
about this and I don't think Russia will
be cautious about this because they are
worried about the western reaction. No,
no, no, no, no. Russia will be cautious
about this because they will be wor they
will be worried about the presence of
Chinese troops in close proximity or in
contact with Russian troops with access
to Russian military equipment
because the Chinese troops will be
spies.
Russia will see it as a red flag, not
the West. The West may be happy
actually. Okay, the Chinese are playing
games with Russia now. They'll be happy.
I think Russia will see this as as a red
flag
and uh they may not be in a position to
say no to China but they would be
extremely cautious about this. So Russia
would
probably not reject this but they may
they may impose special conditions on
the on the Chinese troops.
You know they'll have to negotiate a
deal as to what kind what kind of
operational measures will be taken and
what kind of operational freedom the
Chinese troops will be given. I don't
think China will agree to Chinese troops
being under Russian command because that
is a sovereignty red flag. I think this
is a highly unlikely scenario. I think
China first of all won't propose this
and even if the proposed Russia Russia
may be very very cautious or suspicious
about such a proposal from China. Would
the west see a red flag if Russia
accepted? I think they would see a red
flag anyway. Yeah. And that would
actually give the west multiple excuses
to to sanction China and China doesn't
need this right now or want this at this
time. So that's where we are. Okay.
Gayora TV says, "Do you think that India
possesses or is in the process of having
space-based DEWs? There's chatter about
some project Kali. What's a DEW?
Directed energy weapon. What's a
directed energy weapon? It's typically
weapons that use photons as a weapon.
What's a photon? A photon is a quantum
of light. It's a wave packet.
Essentially, it's like lasers.
Okay. Lasers. What's laser? It's just
light. Light emission by
synchronized emission of radiation,
right? Yeah. Laser.
Yeah. Kind of. So
population inversion what I don't know
okay that's not relevant here. So a
laser is a directed energy weapon. You
use energy in the form of light okay as
the weapon and you can have u various
kinds of such weapons. Um so the
question then is so that now we have
understood what a directed energy weapon
is. It's like a light beam essentially
or a beam of photons. It could be
ultraviolet, infrared, whatever. But
energy which is being used as a weapon.
So that's a DEI. Now does India have
spacebased DEIs? I think India does have
landbased DEIS very powerful
land-based DEIS. Space- based I doubt it
very much.
First of all, let's see what kind of
landbased DEIS India has. India directed
energy weapons. So we do have um
DRDO projects like Kali microwaves,
Sudia high powered lasers, Sahastra
Shaki weapon mounted laser laser etc. We
have pretty powerful uh DEIS kilo ampere
linear injector uses electron beams to
generate microwaves to soft kill
electronics and drones and missiles with
potential for future upgrades. Shahustra
Shaki 30 kilowatt vehicle mounted laser
system that successfully neutralized
drones. It's been tested up to 5 km away
demonstrating real world capability.
Surya 300 kowatt high power laser system
targeting aerial threats like missiles
at longer ranges up to 20 km. Very very
very good. Excellent. I like it. Adita
gas dynamic laser demonstrator on a
vehicle for terminal missile defense.
Laser dazzlers. Okay, that's fine for
crowd control. Dura 2. Uh we're not sure
what that is. Directionally unrestricted
ray gun array. Uh yeah, so all these
strategic u you know objectives what you
can do with it. And uh the great thing
is that you don't need ammunition for
this. You just need energy.
Um you may need capacitors and all that.
Okay, you don't need ammunition for
this. Now these are pretty massive
systems. Okay.
And uh typically this would weigh
hundreds of kilograms potentially. How
do you launch that into space? Yeah,
sure we can launch several hundred
kilograms into space, even thousands of
kilograms. But uh
We most likely don't have that. So
recently we've been we've been trying to
launch some uh military satellites or or
critical strategic satellites into space
and it's not worked out right very well.
Uh and we we we hardly launch five or
six space missions a year and we
typically announce what those space
missions are. It's not always military
satellites. Sometimes your standard
communication satellites are sometimes
something like Chundrian or Mongalan or
whatever.
So I therefore doubt very strongly that
we have any space-based directed energy
weapons. If India was a nation that
launched dozens of space missions a year
then we could easily
quietly launch something and not you
know people won't realize but when you
launch just five or six space missions a
year everything is scrutinized and it's
very very very hard to to to camouflage
the launch of a DEI uh system into space
so I doubt that we have that India has
space-based DEIS
we hung Kuran says is no
uh India is developing ramjet powered
artillery shells if it is successful how
significant will it be for our defense
capabilities my super chat but watching
since 5 years I learned a lot oh
outstanding thank you so much thank you
so much for being for having been a
viewer for 5 years thank you so much
really appreciate that um now right so
uh yeah I've heard recent recently the
news came out that we are developing
ramjet powered artillery shells so
what's What's a ramjet? A ramjet is a
special kind of uh of propulsion system.
Uh what's the application it what's the
application of ramjets? One example is
Brahmos.
The brahos missile employs ramjet
engines and these ramjet engine this
ramjet engine on a brahmos missile
accelerates it to mark 2 which is twice
the speed of sound. Right? It's a pretty
massive missile and with this powerful
uh engine that accelerates the missile
to Mach 2. So, Ramjet technology, Ramjet
engines
accelerate
projectiles to very high speeds,
typically M2, sometimes Mach 3 also. And
then you one step beyond ramjets is
scramjets which is supersonic combusting
supersonic combusting ramjets which
takes you to Mac 5 plus. So the news is
that India is developing ramjet powered
artillery shells. So what's an artillery
shell? It's a projectile
that is shot out of a cannon or an
artillery or a howitzer or an artillery
piece. Right? So what does a artillery
shell look like? Let me first show that.
Okay. Artillery.
Artillery shell. So that's what an
artillery shell typically looks like.
Yeah, it's got this super uh this this
this uh streamlined aerodynamic shape
and you have artillery shells that come
in different sizes and shapes. Mostly
the shapes are similar but the sizes are
different and then you have artillery
shells with fins and whatnot and some
artillery so so artillery shells don't
typically have a motor an engine that
propels it. It doesn't leave behind a
jet. It's simply shot out of um of the
tube of the artillery piece and that's
it. Then it then it just goes on a
ballastic trajectory and impacts the uh
the destination.
But now we have this artillery shell
which will have ramjets.
So what that does is it's going to
extend the ra range of the artillery
shell. It's going to kind of turn the
artillery shell into an extended rocket
kind of thing. And the power it
delivers, you know, the speed at which
it will impact the the the the the
target is going to be higher than a
typically typical artillery shell. So
what's the advantage of this?
First of all, extended range. Let's say
you have an artillery gun that can fire
a shell to 20 km, but maybe with a
ramjet you can fire it to maybe 30 km,
maybe maybe 40 km. I don't know. I don't
know what the specifics are, but it
extends the range. If you have an
artillery shell with that sort of range,
you may be able to possibly double the
range. Maybe maybe even beyond that. Who
knows? That's one thing. And secondly,
the kinetic energy it carries will be
higher because it's it's traveling
faster.
So that sort of thing. Yeah. So it's
obviously good for our defense
capabilities. It's not a gamecher, but
it's definitely excellent.
Right. Okay. So yeah, thank you Vihank
for the super chat and nice to have
finally had communication with you.
Thank you.
Just kidding says namaste sir. Well,
namaste G. Namaste back to you. Thank
you so much. Thank you. Honey Sharma
says I know you don't watch Indian
movies but you must you must watch
Tumbad. Tumb. I I used to think it was
Tumbad based on the English spelling tu
mb. I was like what what does toubad
mean? But then someone told me it is
tumb.
Okay. Uh yeah
and so you must watch tumb and it's
based on Indian goddess and monsters.
It's a beautifully crafted movie. Please
watch. Um yeah, I never got the
opportunity to watch it on the big
screen and I've heard a lot of really
good things about it. Like it's one of
India's finest uh movies, genuinely
world-class movie. Apparently a
frightening movie and scary horror
stuff. Oh, I'm so scared. But yeah,
thank you for the recommendation. I will
certainly watch it. I it's it's been on
my watch list for like a few years, but
I somehow never got around to watching
it. So, thank you for the reminder. I
will certainly find the time to watch
that movie. Thank you. Slow cheita.
Well, we had fast snail, now we have
slow cheita.
I love this uh this creative usernames.
Okay. Which Indian emperor was strong in
terms of power projection?
Oh, well see
when we talk about pro power projection
in the modern day era we're talking
about missiles we're talking about
military bases we're talking about naval
bases across the world we're talking
about satellite systems we're talking
about cyber capabilities right 21 20th
century and 21st century technologies
that's what has enabled nations like the
US especially in the US to project power
globally now you go back to the 19th
century
The only way to project project power
was by having a very powerful and
capable navy and using the navy to
enforce the control of sea lanes and the
protection of strategically uh placed
ports
and those ports would also serve as
points of extraction from the colonies
from the occupied nations. like you had
ports in India which were places where
from which you know all the all the
resources of India were extracted out of
India and sent to the sent to various
parts of the world. So that's how you
did power projection now in India.
So that's 19th 18th 19th centuries.
Before that you had traders like Indian
traders who would trade with East Africa
etc. Um but those were trading missions.
Those were not power projection
missions. So if you ask me what Indian
emperor was strong in terms of power
projection when it come who was the last
great Indian emperor. The last great
Indian empire was the Marata Empire and
it was one of the great uh
advantages it had was it it had a very
powerful navy. So the Marata Empire was
able to project power across India's
coastline. Right? So that that's one.
Apart from that the Gupta emperors had
pretty powerful navies. Obviously there
was no air force in back in the day. You
had infantry, you had
and you had cavalry and you had navy. So
when Samudra Gupta
uh conquered the Deken region all the
way to you know the south southern part
of India, it was a two-pronged invasion.
It was a land-based invasion plus a sea
based invasion. So Samodra Gupta was
very powerful in in that sense. Apart
from that um power projection was all
landbased. when it comes to for example
I suppose various Indian emperors also
were able to project power through the
through naval means into the straight of
Horbos etc but most of those records
have disappeared we've lost those but
yeah we did have that during the time of
the Mahakhatraas you know the Indoskeian
rulers of western India especially
Gujarat Sarashtra Maharashtra that
region uh even Rajasthan and so on those
those Mahakhatra rulers like Rudra Daman
etc. Nahana, Chashtana, Rudra Daman etc.
These great kings they also had powerful
navies. They controlled the great
western ports of India the ports in
Gujarat and Sarashtra through which we
traded with the west and that's why the
Mahakhatra was very were very powerful
and very u um very wealthy
and then the Gupta Gupta emperors took
over that part of India they defeated
the Makatraas. Uh so yeah so back in the
day power projection was mainly naval
and when it comes to an emperor like
Kaneska his power projection was all
landbased
so those days we did not have air force
we had some navy that's why power
projection was limited not just in India
everywhere in the world
okay
uh tu says your review on jajnadvam work
now expert try to review his work kushal
look I haven't studied his work in
detail. I have had him on my podcast
and I think he's legit. He he has uh so
the work he has done. Okay. The the work
he's done is essentially the the the
decipherment. Let me find that. Okay.
Give me a second. It is the decipherment
of the uh so-called indust value or
harapans script
and
and he has done it through cryptographic
means by treating the problem as a as a
cryptographic problem and that's a
scientific way of doing it a logical way
of doing it and I'm pretty sure that
what the work he has done is legitimate
uh so if you want to know what podcast
it is on my channel uh if you look here
it is this one ACP91 Abij Chava 91 a
year ago. This one here.
So if you're interested, do do watch
that.
So I I think his his work is legit. I
think his work is great.
But I haven't studied it like rigorously
and go through gone through his entire
process because I've never had the time
to do that. But it makes the most sense
to me
um
to
Okay, it's the same question all over
again. Okay, I just answered that. All
right, thank you sir. Tu thank you. Uh
Naven Ch Johan says India's information
warfare or narrative remains weak across
X, Instagram, YouTube in Reddit. Even
Pakistan outperforms us in narrative
coordination. Why? Because the
government doesn't consider this
whatever reason to be important.
When it comes to the Pakistani um
narrative warfare uh
approach, well, it's the government of
Pakistan that's involved in this. When
it comes to the Chinese narrative
warfare strategy, the government funds
this and coordinates this. The Chinese
government does it. In the case of
India, it is individuals who do it. The
government simply is not interested. Why
is the government of India not
interested in fighting a narrative war
on social media? I don't have the
faintest clue. Every nation has a
propaganda outlet, right? The BBC, it is
the British propaganda outlet. U the
Americans have multiple CNN, Fox News,
they they have various print or or uh
you know uh internet outlets like
whatever New York Times, uh Washington
Post, etc. The Chinese have C CCT CCTN
or whatever. Every nation, the the
Germans have Deutschell. The French have
France France 24. Every nation has these
BBC's, their version of the BBC. India
has nothing. India simply doesn't care
about about fighting a narrative war.
The government of India, it has it has
had all these years to do do something
about it. They simply don't care. I
don't know why they don't care.
this what we have this information and
broadcasting ministry why do we have it
why I I don't get it
so the question is why and I don't have
the answer to this the government of
India simply doesn't care why I think
only they can answer this question I
don't have an answer beats me I'm
clueless I'm stumped stumped by a mile
Singh says planning to watch board of
two no plans to Watch Border 2.
I watched Border One on the big screen
when it came out. Yeah, I It was a
pretty long movie, but overall
satisfying, good movie. Uh I'm not sure
if I should watch Border 2. I I'll I'll
wait for the reviews to come in. Has it
already come out? The movie? I'm not
aware. Uh
yeah, a lot of these movies are
intensely disappointing
when they come out. Like I has come out.
I've not seen it but I've heard not nice
things. Dhandra they all's last movie.
What did he do?
So I'm not sure if I should watch Bord.
If if the if the reviews are good then
then yeah I I may perhaps consider
watching it. Uh Ra Run Rajger says when
when is the last time you you proven
wrong? Uh
when was the last time I was proven
wrong? One of the I don't know exactly
the last time. One example is this. I
was a firm believer in the Arian
invasion theory. I believed it.
I I mean it's what I had been what I had
learned growing up and all the textbooks
said that there was an ar invasion of
India and it just made sense that you
know it must have been like that. I
never really paid attention to it and
and and I used to I used to have these
comments I used to see these comments on
Twitter that you know the RN invasion
thinking theory is wrong and all and I
used to get annoyed. I used to get
annoyed with this people that why does
everything have to be wrong? Why do we
have to question everything?
Then one day I think in 2016 or whatever
I decided to actually examine the
evidence properly.
Not not the textbooks and not the
history books, but the actual history
historical data, the histo the the
archaeological records, the the history,
the research papers, the genetics, the
genetic research papers. I went through
all of that and I was like, what the
hell? I'm completely wrong with this.
It was like the biggest revelation. It
was a complete U-turn for me. 180° turn.
I was completely wrong in my belief that
the iron inversion theory is correct. So
that's one example. I'm sure there must
have been more.
Honey Sharma says, "Why are we so awful
in tests and ODIs recently but dominate
like no one is in T20s? Is it because of
the new coach or something? I can't
see." Well, that's an interesting
cricket question. Look, I um uh first of
all, look, I have never played cricket
uh seriously or professionally. So maybe
I'm not the the expert, but what what do
I see?
Why are we so awful in tests and ODIs
recently? Because we insist on having
crap wickets,
low bouncing, hard turning wickets,
bad wickets, terrible wickets. You know
the best wickets according to me,
quality wickets. Those are the
Australian wickets. They are hard and
bouncing wickets. I've I've been I've
seen various Indian teams tour Australia
over the years since the since the early
'90s. And what I've always seen in in
the past, not recent 232s, but in the
past is that the first three, four
matches, the Indian batsman always
struggle because it's hard and bouncing,
they can't handle the bounce. But once
they get the hang of the bounce, it they
play superbly especially quality batsmen
like you know Lakshman and Draid and
Tendulkar, even Seag and so on. Did I
miss some names? I'm sure must have
missed some names. But high quality
batsmen, they love those hard bouncing
wickets. They play superbly there. in
Kohli. Ki Kohley is another another
example. So you need quality wickets.
Okay. What's a quality? What's the
definition of a quality wicket? A high
quality wicket. A high quality wicket is
a is a wicket on which highquality
batsmen will get runs and high quality
bowlers will get wickets. But poor
batsmen will struggle and poor bowlers
will struggle. That's a high quality
wicket. It's balanced.
Now look at India's wickets. The kind of
Indian wickets India produces in test
matches. rubbish wickets, wickets that
crumble in in like within a day and then
this this start spinning viciously. When
you have a dibbly doubly bowler like Joe
Rut who who could take wickets or or
who's the latest South African guy who
came and took so many wickets a
part-time off spinner takes wickets like
like his mutan
when you have part-time bowlers becoming
life-threatening that's the exa that's
an example of a very bad wicket
and in seam bowling terms when you have
Phil Simmons bowling 10 overs for three
runs and taking four wickets that's a
very poor fast bowling wicket so you
need to have a balanced wicket
that is challenging but fair and that's
what we would like to see in test
matches and if you produce these third
rate wickets then then others will take
advantage of that and T20s it's okay
it's good to see T20s but the real test
m test of high quality cricket is test
matches and we have been doing poorly of
late uh is it because of the new coach
something I can't see I mean
we we look at our bowling attack we have
one world class bowler Bumra right we
don't have any other world class bowler
right now Shami is world class but he
has been kept out for whatever reason
why isn't has he been kept out why
he was the best bowler of the 2023 world
cup he should have been the man of the
series not kohi he bulldozed every
opposition on Indian wickets
so why is he not in the team I don't get
it so that clearly seems to be something
beyond
merit
Why? So we have world class spin
bowlers. We have Ravi Jadea. Who else do
we have? Whoever it may be. Um Kulp,
we have Bumrah fast world class fast
bowl. One of the greatest of all time.
Of course. Shami is also a great bowler
but he's not there. So who do we have?
We have Prasid, we have Siraj, we have
uh Harshett. Those are good bowlers but
not great. So there's many problems
and maybe something to do with the coach
perhaps. I mean I'm a big fan of Gambir
especially as a player who was a great
player for a while. Not the not the best
of all time but definitely a very hard
worker and all. Um but yeah something's
wrong needs to be fixed. There's a
there's something wrong with the
mindset. You should have high quality
wickets.
Anyhow that's a good diversion into
cricket.
Okay, let's get back into on track.
Okay, Sergeant Skylin says, "Slow. Sorry
to clarify my earlier question regarding
Trump's term. Good for India. Like, will
India use this opportunity to make
reforms?" Oh, well, a an external
challenge is often a great opportunity
for a nation to make reforms to to solve
internal problems.
So, will it will India use it? Will
India use this opportunity that we have
external pressure? Will we use this
opportunity to make internal reforms?
Well, I don't know. That depends on the
government and the leadership
that I can't tell. I can tell you what
approach Trump will have towards India.
It's going to be a hard approach.
So that I can tell you what India's
response will be will be towards that.
the the the reforms we need are major
reforms and uh well those can be
unpopular in the short term politically
unpopular in the short term will the
government of India have
the wherew withhold to make such reforms
you know see major reforms deep deep
rooted reforms pay dividends only in the
wrong long run you won't see immediate
returns for
But that's what we need. And shortterm
you will have pain. If you if you do
reforms that will only bring
the results in the long run, it means
there are going to be short-term pain.
You go to gym for the first time. You're
going to be in pain for 3 weeks. Every
muscle fiber will hurt. But long term
it's going to be great for you. But do
you have do you have that in you to
withstand those three weeks of pain? Or
maybe two weeks, whatever. Depends.
So uh I'm not sure if India will use the
opportunity to take the to make the
reforms. I'm not sure.
Vihung Kuran says is nuclear energy a
good alternative for rocket and missile
propulsion compared to chemical rockets
considering its success in submarines.
Totally different matter. A submarine is
a totally different thing.
Okay. In submarine, you have a
miniaturized nuclear reactor that drives
a se steam engine essentially
that gives r gives gives the energy the
electrical energy to the submarine and
the propulsive energy to its to its
propeller.
Okay, that's a massive thing that
nuclear reactor even if it's a
miniaturized nuclear reactor it weighs a
lot weighs a lot. Now a nuclear reactor
is a very expensive thing. Costs a lot
of money.
And if you use a nuclear reactor in a
rocket or in a missile, you you want to
launch let's say 300 missiles every day.
Can you have 300 nuclear reactors? First
of all, how much money that will spend?
How much money will you lose in that?
And you can't have a nuclear so small
it'll fit into a into the backside uh
posterior side of a missile.
Um so yeah it's it's not a great
alternative but but but but we're still
discussing rocket propulsion. Well
there's two kinds of nuclear rocket
propulsion.
One
is simply nuclear detonations. You need
a very massive rocket for that. Okay.
And you can launch a rocket using
nuclear detonations, pulsed nuclear
detonations. There was this this this
project in the 1960s or something to
Mars by a bomb or something. I I don't
remember what what it was called. Give
me a second. Sorry. What is this?
Um, give me a second. Let's Google this.
So, you can do that. Okay. uh to Mars by
a bomb.
Project Orion. Project Orion.
So, uh what was this? Project Orion.
Nuclear propulsion. Okay. It was a study
conducted a series of atomic explosions
behind the craft. So, you're actually
detonating nuclear bombs behind the
craft. You need a very massive craft
craft for that. So, yeah, it's it's
theoretically possible. Theoretically
works. Another
way of having nuclear propulsion in a
rocket or a missile is to have a nuclear
ramjet.
Okay, that essentially can give a rocket
or a missile unlimited range. You can
keep it flying for months. Nuclear
ramjet. Would you like to see that?
Okay, I'll show you. A nuclear ramjet.
And the Russians have such a missile.
Nuclear ramjet project Pluto.
uh nuclear ramjet and Russian
Russian nuclear ramjet. So the Russians
have this bur snick. That's right. So
they have this uh so near unlimited
range and low altitude stealthy flight
and so on. Yeah. Uh but once again this
is going to be pretty expensive. Each
each missile is going to be pretty
pretty expensive because you actually
have a nuclear reactor inside it. So
it's possible but it's pretty expensive
and
it's not something you want to do on a
large scale.
Rashid Rashit Shawastu says Indians take
pride in juggard. We need to fix it. See
every every problem doesn't have a
juggard solution but jard is a good tool
to have in your toolkit. Jard means you
means improvisation right? You improvise
you somehow find a solution. It may be a
stop gap solution. It may not be the
most elegant solution. It may be a
temporary solution or whatever. But you
somehow make it work. That is a good
tool to have in the toolkit. But it
should not be the only tool we have in
the toolkit. Unfortunately, the things
way things are in India sometimes it's
the only tool that people have.
So it's good to have it. But we need to
think of long-term solutions also.
So yeah, I agree with you that we need
to fix this mentality of only doing
juggard for everything. I agree.
Rahul says, "With with the UAE getting
closer to Bat, do you foresee more Arab
nations doing so? With Oman's good
relations with Bat, can it get can it be
next to get close?"
Um, we have good relations with various
uh nations in the Arabian region.
UAE obviously with the UAE we have
excellent relations. We have a free
trade agreement and we possibly will
have a defense deal with them mutual I
don't know some kind of defense
agreement defense deal a nuclear
cooperation much more and we have a
massive population in the UAE so UAE and
India very good relations do I foresee
other nations uh when it comes to Oman
we already have good relations with Oman
we already have some kind of defense
understanding with Oman have you heard
of dukum well this is not classified so
I can I suppose I can show this it's
obviously
known to the public. Dukum where is
Duke? Uh here we have Dukum. So this is
a port city, port town and we have a
port here. Port of Dukum and u well
India kind of operates some part of this
port. India doesn't operate this port
but India has the um the the permission
to use the port for naval operations or
or or
naval refueling or whatever right uh so
India has excellent relations with e
with with Oman
and uh
so we already have a defense
understanding clearly with Oman
um so it's already close it's not like
it it should be the next to close. It's
already close and uh yeah, I think uh we
are on a very good track when it comes
to these matters. Obviously, Saudi
Arabia is aligning with Pakistan and
with Turkey. So, we have India and and
and uh the UAE and and Israel. That's
that's the other coalition kind of thing
that's that's emerging in this region.
Um and we have good relations with Oman
as well. So, I think we are in good
shape. I am I don't necessarily see
India and Oman
having to get closer than what they
already are.
Riser 199 says how does balkcanize of
India happen process your theory? No, we
don't want this to happen. What is
balkcanization? First of all, what's the
process of balconization? Balkcanization
means the break up of a nation into
multiple multiple pieces. This term
comes from the Balkans region, the
Yugoslavia region. Yugoslavia used to be
one one big country. Now it's broken up
into multiple smaller countries. Serbia,
Kosovo,
Serbia, uh Croatia,
Bosnia,
North Macedonia and so on so forth,
right? U balconization. So how does this
happen? It happens in it can happen
various a variety of ways. U the
Americans simply broke up Yugoslavia
through military force essentially.
um and the Chinese and even the
Americans would like India to be
balconized. So how how did it happen in
1947? That's also a bulcanization
process, right? Historically Gandhar was
split off from India by invaders, by
occupiers. So that was the first
bulcanization of India.
1935 the British broke off Burma from
India. Second bulcanization.
Then Sri Lanka whenever it happened and
then 47 was Pakistan east and west
Pakistan. So these are processes of
balconization. You can have
bulcanization through multiple ways. One
this is one example.
GG Gosavi says why has no country tried
color revolutions in the US despite them
abusing minorities too. US is probably
most susceptible as the mistreat
natives, blacks etc.
The US is too powerful. That's why this
answer is so simple. The US is just too
powerful.
It's not like I mean it's not like okay
let's do bulcanization or let's do color
revolution and it'll happen.
The process of a color revolution is a
very long stepby-step process with in
which you to to to create the right
conditions on the ground. You have to
you to cultivate people. You have to you
have to you have to cultivate traitors
in the country. You have to cultivate
media organizations. You have to
cultivate uh uh NOS's you have to
infiltrate the country deeply
and then create fake movements and all
it's a very long process why has the
America why has the US never tried this
in India they kind of did a test run in
2019 the the Shahin bag thing and Delhi
rights and all that they did a test run
of course because India is deeply
penetrated and compromised in a variety
of ways so But it's not easy. It's very
difficult. Right? That's why
Aries Manticor says LLMs are just the
start. They're going semantic next.
Let me tell you, let me tell you
something interesting perspective.
One of the world's biggest AI companies
is Tesla.
Tesla doesn't have LLM.
What does the Tesla AI do?
What what what kind of training data is
used to to train the Tesla AI,
recordings
of Tesla cars, video recordings. The
Tesla cars, they have this video um they
they record video, right? Self-driving
video and all that or or manual driving
video. So all of that every every day
probably hundreds of thousands of hours
of video are recorded.
All of that is used to train the Tesla
the Tesla AI to create a properly
genuinely auto autonomous self-driving
system.
So there are various ways of creating
AIS. LLMs it's just one one kind of AI
all kinds of AIS
died in plane crash says a family member
went to Sri Lanka told that roads there
are much better than in India. Is being
an independent nation good for its
people as they don't have to suffer
under our Babuam?
Uh it's an advantage they have that they
don't have to suffer under the kind of
conditions we have. Uh why are roads bad
in India. Um I think the roads that come
under the central government typically
are better than the roads that come
under certain state governments.
The the re real reason why roads are bad
in India in some parts of India is the
alleged corruption. Alleged entirely
alleged corruption that allegedly
exists. Let's say you hypothetically
allegedly allocate a 100 cr for a road
project. How much of that money is
actually used allegedly to build the
road?
And where do the cuts allegedly go?
That's the reason
allegedly
Aries Manticor says why didn't we create
our own modern political philosophy to
be taught in universities rather than
communism, socialism, feminism, etc. a
growing poison that fundamentally does
not ally with us.
To create a modern political philosophy
based in based rooted in our
civilizational values, you need
highquality original thinkers. Which
institution
is supposed to produce highquality
original thinkers? It's your education
system.
What is the quality of your education
system? It's third rate garbage. It is
trash. It seeks out,
identifies and destroys talent and it
promotes mediocrity. If somebody is a
highly original thinker, it'll seek out
and destroy that person.
That's your answer. That's why I keep
saying that we have we must reform our
education system top to bottom.
This is your answer.
Right? You can't have original
highquality worldclass top- class
thinkers with a third rate education
system. You may have such people who are
naturally brilliant and talented, but
the education system will sideline them.
It'll never allow them to have a voice.
It'll drown them in the rat race.
That's your answer. Arismantic or sir,
ma'am, whatever. Okay. Uh ICMBB says,
"What's the future of channel? Can we
contribute? You are contributing just by
being my viewers and by interacting with
me. The future is
whatever we seeing now now is the
future.
Uh there is no massive future plan as as
in I'll do something completely
drastically different or something. uh
we this channel is about me interacting
with you all
and uh us exploring and understanding
the world together the past present and
future from three lenses history
geopolitics science and that's what we
continue doing maybe in the future I may
do something somewhat different maybe
people have been suggesting I restart
the understanding America series or
maybe I I create standalone videos like
I used to do before maybe I'll take that
up. But overall, it it's going to be the
way it is right now mostly.
Arismantic says the IIAF released
statements that we can't miss miss the
next fighter jet fighter jet
generational leap. We need to either
join the French German FCAS or German
Japanled Tempest programs from which we
at least start our own program. So what
happens to the AMCA the advanced medium
combat aircraft? Isn't that a fifth
generation fighter plane? Why do we need
to partner with the French and Germans
or the Japanese?
Or why can't we do it on our own? I
think I think this is highly perplexing.
Why does a very all technology have to
come from abroad? Why do why do all
systems have to come from abroad? Why do
we have to partner with foreigners for
the for the for some people to be happy?
uh this way we will always be be you
know dependent on foreign technology and
subordinate to foreigners.
So I I don't get this if if this
statement is is is has actually been
released by the IF it's perplexing in
that case perplexing.
Mclovin says, "Why has the US and Russia
never been in a direct war?" Because a
direct war between the US and Russia
will inevitably
lead to a nuclear exchange because
things escalate. And up the escalation
ladder, we have things we don't want to
use. So, historically, it's been the
USSR, now it's Russia. But Russia has
the same nuclear arsenal and maybe a
better nuclear arsenal, more augmented
nuclear arsenal. So, that's why it
doesn't make any sense for them to ever
be in a direct war. That's why it's
always been proxy conflicts.
Ashoto Debar says in the 1820s Thomas
Mandro's survey of indigenous education
of in India reported castwise
composition of students and teachers
suggesting wide representation thoughts
no surprise no surprise all these
stories see first of all these four
casts were instituted in India at the
end of the 19th century or maybe the
beginning of the 20th century that's
when the British mandated that every
India Indian must identify with one of
the forecasts before that you had Vera
and Jati. Vera is the four-fold division
which pe people roughly had some idea of
but what they really ident identified
with was the jati the jati right you had
thousands maybe tens of thousands of
jatis in India
and it was the jati that was more
important than the vera or the cast the
cast it's a foreign term for India now
like you say Thomas Mandro survey of
indigenous education we have we had our
own indigenous education system in India
based in temples the great universities
has been destroyed a thousand years ago
in around 1000 AD but we still had
temples at the grassroots that survived
and continued the Indian education
system and that's that's where the
survey was done in various temples right
and various partialas and what what not
right and what they found what Thomas
Monro found was you had wide
representation not just various
so-called casts vernas and jatis but
also both genders boys and girls were
also equally represented so all this
all all this atrocity literature of
India being a castist uh oppressive
unequal society it's all lies and beyond
that I I I would recommend um
uh read this thing okay the the
daral daral
daral um what beautiful tree
the beautiful tree okay uh indigenous
Indian educ ation in the 18th century.
Read this. It's not one book. It's a
series of I think two three books.
Okay. And that will
I mean if you read that you will
understand that we had the world's best
education system. The British ruined a
beautiful thing. Everybody
was given education. All the so-called
casts,
boys as well as girls. Everybody was
educated.
And education was typically free.
You had no monthly fees and tutori.
The British ruined a beautiful thing and
today your teachers will tell you that
the British brought education to India.
Here
is Mantor says actually we have recently
privatized the space sector. Is the
government of India trying to create
more players alongside ISRO to
eventually reach the frequency of
launches you mentioned? They suspect
sabotage too. I don't know if the
government of India suspects sabotage.
Obviously, they should they should
investigate that. Now, we have recently
privatized the space sector is in in the
sense that we have now allowed private
companies uh to to participate in the
space sector. Some of the companies can
simply produce spare parts or or spares
or or components for ISRO rockets. Um
and some space space companies can start
you know developing their own rocket
technology technologies or whatever. We
have various companies that are trying
to do that. Skyroot is a good example
right um it's good but this the private
space sector is currently in its infancy
infancy. Okay. It's it's just starting
off. Uh you can't if you have a private
space sector that's in in its infancy,
you can't you can't use that as a
justification to bring the number of
launches of ISRO down to from maybe 20,
30, maybe 10, 20 to five.
Let the space the private sector mature.
Give it 10 years, 15 years, 20 years
typically minimum 10 years. And once
they can start launching rockets and
satellites on their own, then you can
have ISRO do other things.
Right. Right now the private se space
sector is in its infancy. It's taking
baby steps.
This is not the time to bring the
frequency of launches of ISRO down.
Doesn't make any sense whatsoever.
That's that's the issue. That's the
issue. You see,
Honey Sharma says, "I think something is
wrong with me. I'm preparing for CAT 26.
I really want to study for hours, but
after an hour, my brain is fried." Uh,
continue. If I take a break, that turns
into hours and the next thing I know I'm
watching Netflix the rest of the day to
be continued. And not to forget, I
usually feel sleepy when I try to study.
My vitamin B and D are in check more or
less. What do I do?
Um,
what do you do?
Well, that's that's a major problem
you're having. So, clearly it's not an
issue with your vitamin levels. They
seem to be fine. I suppose you've done
your blood work or whatever you've test
checked your vitamin and other levels it
seem to be fine. Um when you try to
study you feel sleepy but when you watch
Netflix you can watch it the watch it
all day. So what does it mean? What do
you do? It means that you are not
interested in what you're ma what you're
having to study. It doesn't interest you
right. It doesn't motivate you.
So the
What can you do about that? Um I I would
actually need to know more about you
before I can give you a solution because
I don't know what you're studying. I
don't know how relevant it is to your
life. Sometimes you you get into various
study programs because your parents
pushed you pushed you into it. Maybe you
want to do something else
and you have been pushed into it
unwillingly. You have no choice but to
accept what your parents forced you
forced you into. So you get into the
course and then but your heart is
somewhere else. Maybe you want to do
something else. Maybe they're pushing
you to be a lawyer, but you wanted to be
a doctor. Maybe they're pushing you to
be a doctor, but you wanted to be um an
entrepreneur. I don't know, right? Or
maybe you just don't know what's at the
end of the tunnel. If I get this degree,
then what happens? What do I do with my
life? And you have no idea. And that's
why you're not getting the motivation.
So, what you have to do is first find
some kind of goal for yourself. Whatever
age you're at, give go forward 10 years
and imagine what kind of life you want
to live.
What kind of work do you want to be
doing in 10 years time? Ideally, best
case scenario, how much money do you
want to have? And then work work
backwards. How do I reach there? And
does this study program that I'm doing
help me in that? If it does not, then
maybe it's not the right thing for you.
And if it does help you, then maybe this
this big goal motivates you towards
that. So that's typically how we do it.
Very often in India what you find is
many students who are pushed into things
that they have no interest in uh because
parents know that you know you've got to
be safe in life you got to have a job
and so on and maybe yeah so you've got
to work things out for yourself that's
what you have to do you to figure out
what is your big goal in life you have
to reverse engineer the the success and
figure out how do I reach that step by
step and then once you have this the a
rough idea of how others have done it in
the past sort of achievement you know
then you can figure out whether you are
on the right track or not do I need to
study this nonsense or is it actually
useful for me if it's useful then it's
not nonsense then go for it study then
you're motivated otherwise drop it and
do whatever is right for you along the
path but always have a plan B and plan C
okay don't put all your eggs in one
basket so that's the deal okay sir Anish
Sharma thank you and all the best I wish
you well I wish you well I wish you
success all the
Karthikaya says why don't we why don't
have hundreds of cha chavdas sidek
sudanchis across the country busting
propagandas and myth the more the
marrier uh why don't we have more of
people such as these um I never thought
about it why don't we have them uh see
I'll tell you what I wasn't produced by
the education system of India okay I am
not a product of the education system I
did go through the Indian education
system some various times in my life but
it hasn't made me who I am. I am
entirely self-made. So I suppose other
people like this will be safe self-made
potentially possibly. I don't know.
Okay. I don't know what has been the
life trajectory of the people you're
mentioning here. For me it's been like
that. I am not a product of the
education system. I am entirely
self-made. Everything I've learned I've
done in my own no one's taught me a
thing. So that is I suppose a little
rare in life. And maybe that's why we
have fewer people like these. I suppose
that could be one answer to your
question perhaps possibly. I'm just
speculating here.
Aries Manticor says many secular people
uh trying to tell us to think critically
about the positive contributions of the
muggles that are not taught to us.
Critically I say strangled economy,
terrorist population, what else? I mean
I can't think of any significant
positive contributions of the muggles.
They were foreign occupiers.
And if you say they were born in India
and they had Indian mothers or whatever,
Orurangev was born in India. He would
have had Indian female ancestors. What
was he? He was a monster. He was a
barbarian was a terrorist. So I don't
know what real positive contributions
they did. So my suggestion, my
recommendation is ignore these secular
people.
Critical thinking. They're going to
teach you crit critical thinking.
Really? They're teaching you the
opposite. They are recommending you do
the opposite of critical thinking and
ignore the evidence that's staring us in
the face. Right? Ignore such people.
Arismantic says we need to not only
reform policy but institutional capture
with the right people. We should have
learned this from the Soviets would have
made our bureaucracy a fast and mean
machine unlike the Babuam.
I agree with you. I agree with you. But
uh reforms are are difficult. They're
hard and they're painful. You're going
to have face push back from the people
from the people who are invested in the
system from the people who benefit from
the system. They won't let you make the
do the reforms. They will resist the
reforms. Let's say you want to reform
the bureaucracy. Let's say you bring in
one new rule only one new rule that a
bureaucrat can be actually fired for uh
for non-performance or for for doing
something harmful. Right now you can
only suspend a bureaucrat and then the
bureaucrat is generally after the
suspension period of one week, one month
or whatever brought back into work. You
can't fire, you can't terminate a
bureaucrat's
uh employment, right? You can only
suspend them. Suspension is a joke.
Let's say you bring in a new law that
says that now instead of suspending we
can fire people. We can turbulent
employment permanently.
What will happen? I imagine the entire
bureaucracy will go on strike and the
whole country will be paralyzed. Then
what does the government do?
They can't do a thing. These are issues,
right? Major issues. The people who
benefit from this rotten system, they
won't they won't give in easily.
They they'll try their best to stop
reforms from happening. Then what
happens? Prime Minister has to roll back
reforms and issue an apology. How does
it look? Best not try these things. You
see that's the problem
are Raju Run.
Okay. The question is can you tell about
the hindrance kovacin faced even though
it's better that than it's better than
many by who and west big farmer afraid
UK quarantined coaxined
Mexico politics etc we may have given
for cheap or free okay I am not very
very deeply
um
uh I I I don't know much about this
um I I'm obviously aware of coax vac
it's it's the vaccine India developed
indigenously
and it's not an RNA based vaccine
messenger messenger RNA vaccine it's a
standard you know good old-fashioned
vaccine
uh the good old fashioned vaccines are
typically vaccines that use either
disabled or partial viral sequences
what's a virus there are various ways of
looking at a virus
a virus is something it's an organism
that is
it exists on the boundary between living
and non-living. It has some properties
of living beings and some properties of
non-living beings. It's on the boundary.
But one of the properties viruses have
that are that of living beings is that
it has DNA or RNA. That is something
non-living beings don't have. Right? So
that's a virus. But viruses typically
have short genetic sequences. DNA or
RNA. They're like genetic ideas.
genetic ideas, bits of ideas floating
around. So, so typically in a
old-fashioned vaccine, what you do is
you take a disabled virus that can't
really in hurt you or you take a partial
fragmented virus or whatever and you you
use that to make the body familiar with
the virus and develop the antibodies
needed to fight off the viral infection.
That's your standard old fashion fashion
vaccine and that's what coaxin is the
messenger DNA vaccine that Fiser and
others have produced. My goodness, I
don't know what I that is that is
frightening. You don't want that in your
system. And that's that's it looks like
you know in the past when I used to talk
about corona virus or COVID on this
channel you would get a disclaimer below
the video and all even on even on
Spotify now it's not the case. I'm glad
it looks like the Fiser vaccine has
killed more people than it has saved
right um and the Americans wanted India
to allow the Fiser vaccine in India and
India insisted on user trials and they
they said we don't we will not do user
trials. I mean what why will you not do
user trials get lost so that's why the
Fiser vaccine was not allowed in India
thankfully and that's why we are in
better shape that's what I know I don't
know about the hindrance and all that
that that story I'm not aware of so
Bihung says if we develop large language
models using Indian languages and data
can it then be used to decipher an
unknown language belonging to some
Indian language language family can AI
be used to decipher unknown languages
absolutely
Absolutely it can.
Yeah, that's the answer. If we develop
large language models using Indian
languages, see all Indian languages are
interconnected. North Indian, South
Indian, East Indian, West Indian, all
Indian languages have connections, deep
connections going back thousands of
years. Going back to ancestral
languages, some of which are no longer
spoken, many of which are no longer
spoken. Right?
So if you train LLMs on these languages
with all the texts we have, they'll be
able to decipher any unknown language
that is part of these language families.
Even
languages that are only that are less
related or far away with with distant
relations like you know
let's say the LM has never come across
for example the Irish language. You give
it the Irish language, it may be able to
quickly decipher that. Even if it's only
been trained on the the Indian indoor
and and the so-called tidian languages,
it'll be able to decipher that. So yeah,
yeah, it can certainly be used to
decipher unknown languages.
Aurora Thornne says Dr. Sarah Payne from
the US Naval College says the root of
Russia and China's problems are that
they are continental powers. So they
always underperform naval powers like
the UK, Japan and US thoughts. India
look Dr. Sarah Payne is employed by the
US Naval College and she has to say
things that are well that make the US
look good. Oh, you will see this. I've
seen a few of her snippets of whatever
she says.
She consistently
shows the US is the greatest power, the
most benevolent power and so on. In
Russia, and China, these are kind of
incompetent nations and so on. Right? So
whatever she says, you have to take it
with the understanding that she's
employed by the US Naval College and it
is it is her job to put forth a certain
narrative and she's deeply invested in
that.
So um I watched a few videos and I just
got got the got the idea of what she's
trying to achieve. N it's all right.
Dr. Dr. Sarapin, I'm sure she's
high quality scholar, very knowledgeable
and so on and also very intelligent and
that's a great combination, isn't it?
Uh, hyphen says, "Thank you." Thank you
so much. Hyphen G, thank you so much.
Vihank says, "Thank you for answering
all my questions. You're most welcome.
I've been watching the channel since you
posted the video on best books in Indian
history." Well, that well well that's a
long time. That's probably the first
video I put out, right? Uh, thank you
for reigniting the love towards learning
within me. Thank you so much for being
one of the first viewers of this channel
I suppose. Thank you so much. I really
appreciate that and uh I look without
you viewers without you all this channel
would not be relevant. So I would thank
like to thank you Vihang and thank all
of the viewers for your viewership for
your support for just being here right
thank you so much everyone and to you
also especially you Vihang thank you
IPK1s says Babuam and reservations why
AMCA etc never happened.
Yeah. Well, why was the Theis fighter
delayed?
It the the the project came out in the
early 80s, right? The Theis fighter jet
is a replacement for the MiG 21. The MIG
20 was Mig 21 was finally retired I
think last year.
The project came out in the early 80s.
It was delayed over and over again.
Why was it delayed so many times?
Because the requirements were changed
randomly.
I'm I'm just giving a hypothetical
representational example here. not
necessarily what happened. That's the
requirement is that the jet fighter has
to be 11 m long. Then that's how the
design proceeds. A year later they say
no, it should be 11.3 m long. It's a
completely hypothetical example. Okay,
it's not really what happened. I'm just
saying that's how you can randomly
um change requirements arbitrarily. Then
you say I want the the wings to be
certain dimensions. 6 months later you
say no no I want them to be so some
other dimensions. you keep changing the
requirements the the project can never
take off then funding if the funding
isn't enough sufficient whatever then
how do you manufacture the the
prototypes and so on. So these are the
issues
um that's how you just keep on
indefinitely delaying
um various programs right and uh who
could be behind it? Could it be
politicians? Could it be bureaucrats?
Could it be somebody else? Who knows?
And reservations is a whole different
matter. I completely
uh I think reservations is a really bad
thing. It's good in the short term but
like I keep saying
a permanent solution to a temporary
problem becomes a permanent problem
and that's what India is increasingly
seeing now. We are increasingly putting
we are increasingly creating
permanent solutions to temporary
problems.
Solutions that can't be rolled back. So
they become permanent problems. That's
what India is seeing over and over.
Godliness says yes we face a lot of
problems. Yes we have difficulties but
we are the custodians of the Pashupati
seal and on this republic day like
always we seek the blessings of
Mahabharati in happy republic day. Happy
republic day. Let us be positive. Let us
be optimistic. We have problems. We have
issues. But we shall overcome and we
shall prevail because we are the
custodians of a very very very ancient
civilization. The oldest civilization
that is still in existence and it's at
least 10,000 years old. May it last at
least another 10,000 years more. So let
us do our part. We are one link in this
immense chain and it's our job to ensure
that the future generations have better
opportunities than us. So let's do it.
All right. Great message. Thank you.
Godliness, godliness. Thank you.
Deep says, "Is the gold owned by large
religious institutions in India helping
the country or the economy grow? I was
wondering what the purpose of that
wealth is if it's just stored there
stored there for centuries.
See this wealth was donated to the
temples over centuries maybe thousands
of years by devotees. The temples served
a certain purpose in society of of a
central purpose in society. They were
not merely places of worship, places of
religion and spirituality. They were
educational institutions. Okay? And they
they were so valuable to society and
played such a vital role that people
came and voluntarily donated their gold.
Not just ordinary people but even kings
came
and donated gold. Kings from neighboring
kingdoms. Even in the Sri Pashu Padma
Swami temple you will find coins donated
by Greek kings and whatnot thousands of
years ago.
So that was the purpose for which the
wealth was donated to the temples.
Now what is the use of that wealth in
the temples today? See today we have
a non-Indian constitution
essentially a a dharmic constitution and
a non-Indian non-dharmic system of
governance.
If this wealth is made available to the
politicians what will they use it for? I
wonder. I think we can all imagine.
So this wealth I would say should remain
in the safe custody of the temples
until India becomes
a civilizational nation again in line
with its own civilizational values. Then
let's see how the wealth can be used for
society in
the right way not squandered away and
and dumped into the pockets and bank
accounts of certain certain individuals.
We don't want that to happen today. If
you make this wealth available to the
government, see the government steals
the wealth of so many temples. What is
the wealth used for today?
There are so many temples where the
wealth is stolen by the government
legally.
It is legal. So it's not theft but
actually it's theft. Devotees donate
money to the temple. The government
takes the wealth and uses it for for
doing what? I'll not tell you what. We
all know what the wealth is used for. It
is not used for dharmic purposes.
Right? So we have some temples where
wealth is stored.
We don't want that to be stolen for and
used for essentially anti-vilivilization
purposes. Right? So let it be there for
the future generations and hopefully it
will be good for them, useful for them
if not definitely not for us.
Uh Mangi Kosherit says do you think
India today lacks good parenting?
Uh
look um does India lack good parenting?
That's a pretty interesting question. I
haven't really thought about it. Does
India lack good parenting? Um parents
today typically in at least in cities
have less time for their kids. Kids are
neglected. kids become iPad kids. Gen Z,
Gen Alpha are increasingly uh out of
touch with their culture and so on
because parents have to work so hard and
parents both parents have to work and so
on. Um is that bad parenting? I suppose
it is it is not as good as the previous
generations, right? Um
so I suppose the quality of parenting
and the quality of childhoods have kind
of decreased as the generations have
have gone by. So in the past let's say
in the 1950s and 1960s you would have
had in India mostly extended families
right joint families it used to be
called it's extended families you know
uh
people living with their siblings in one
house all getting married and so on and
you have these extended families being
raised together so kids have access to
their grandparents and aunts and uncles
and nephews and you know cousins and
whatnot and extended big family and it's
a big social environment and you grow up
in a in a big envirment environment like
this you you learn better. Today you
have nuclear families in big cities
where kids aren't socialized the same
way and obviously it's a different
quality of of childhood maybe a poorer
quality quality of childhood. So overall
things have changed I I would not know
for sure whether it's bad or poor
parenting or or less good parenting but
definitely the childhood experience has
changed and it's not changed for the
better.
Okay. YT user says,
"What's your opinion on Europe, the last
battle? Do you think it's propaganda?"
As they say, history is written by
winners. Europa: The Last Battle. I
haven't seen it. It's this massive
documentary, right, about the Second
World War. What is that? Uh,
Europa,
the last battle. What is this? It's
about the Second World War. Uh, 2017
English language Swedish 10 part
neo-Nazi propaganda film. Neo-Nazi
propaganda film. So it I suppose it
glorifies the Nazis and Hitler and so
on. I haven't seen it so I can't say I
haven't seen it. I I believe it's a
pretty massive documentary 10 part was
it 10 part and each part must be at
least an hour long. So it must be like
10 12 hours. So I haven't seen that
answer and say uh Sri Jay Singh says
adversary camp have been tearing the
fabric of India apart cast language
gender religion region government
changes playbook stays since 47 when do
we counter it and how what can the
ordinary people of India do nothing all
you can do is vote and hope for the best
it is the people who we vote for who are
supposed to make things better so what
can India do about this so What India
ideally needs is India needs a new
constitution, a new form of governance,
ideally a presidential form or something
similar, right? A new constitution, a
new form of governance, a new education
system, everything new. Who's going to
do it for us? It can only be the people
who we vote to power. But the people who
vote to power come to power through the
current system. And why will they change
the current system which brought them to
power? So that's the loop we are we are
stuck in. I have no idea how it's going
to be changed. We're going to need a
leader who comes around in once in a
century or once in 500 years. Someone
like Chhatraati Shwaji Maharaj or
somebody like
like Kaneshuka or some other somebody of
that sort somebody like Vishnukta
Chanaga. We don't we don't have anybody
of that stature today. Somebody of the
stature of Lord Krishna or Lord Ram
somebody like that we'll need who can
through sheer will force of will change
everything. as of now uh we I I don't
see any such leader. Yeah, that that
ordinary people can't do a thing. You
can't do a thing without power. So
either you get into politics and acquire
power and change things or you vote and
hope for the best that whoever you are
voting for it does the right thing for
India and that we know how it goes.
Aries mantic horror says global
education levels are falling with the
latest generation especially since chach
JPD may have lost the ability to
critically think are easy to manipulate
no soft skills etc what WTF is going on
it's going on yes
especially with chd especially in India
I mean people have just delegated their
thinking process to chat GPT oh chat GPD
told me so it must be true you know that
sort of thing it's dumbing people down
it. People don't want to think anymore.
Chad GPD, what can I do about this? How
do I solve this problem? Grock, is this
true? That's it. People just don't want
to do any work anymore.
So, it makes people people easier to
manipulate.
It makes easy it makes it easier to lie
to people, to mislead people, to change
governments, to change regimes, to
create a one world government. You see
where where we're going? Uh
P says, does entanglement fully
determine geometry? Not that I know of.
Geometry. No. How can entanglement
determine geometry?
Um, geometry is shapes. Entanglement is
a is a quantum mechanical phenomenon.
It does not in any way determine
geometry that I know of. So no.
Uh, Han Sharma says, "Cat is for MBA and
I want to do it and I have the
motivation to study in the morning but
can't sit for hours." So, you're doing a
CAT common cat. What's a CAT? One
second. What is a CAT? CAT MBA?
CAT MBA. Uh, sorry. MBA. Not MDA. Sorry,
not what is that?
>> M.
>> What's a CAT? Common admission test.
Okay. You want to get into the MD to
into an MBA program. For that, you have
to do a common common admission test.
CAT. And you have the motivation to
study for it in the morning but can't
sit for hours. How can I do it after one
or two I need a break and that turns
into a rabbit hole. I just want to do
it. Earn a ton of money. Okay, so
you want to do it. It motivates you. You
want to to achieve what this gives you
because it will bring you money. So So
then how do you motivate yourself and so
on, right? So okay, so let's say you
study for 1 hour and then you are like
okay, I need a break and then you go and
watch Netflix. Okay, so I'll tell you
what. Don't go and not watch Netflix. Go
and do 50 push-ups or do five push-ups.
Then go for a 10-minute walk. Don't
watch Netflix.
Do some shadow boxing. Yeah. Or or do
something that is physical in nature. Go
for a short run, then come back. That
that will reset your brain, right? Then
you come back and study just 30 minutes
more. So maybe 1 hour is too long for
you. Maybe you need 20 minute sessions.
So do a 20 minute session, then do five
push-ups or do a 20-minut session, then
do a 10-minute jog or a 10-minute walk,
then come back and do it again. So chunk
it down into smaller chunks. That's you
have to try these different techniques.
Make it work somehow. If if you can't
study for hours, I can't study for
hours. I hate it. Right?
So do it that way. Study for let's say
just 20 minutes. Study one topic for 20
minutes. Then go and do five push-ups or
go and do a 10-minute walk. Come back,
do another 20 minute session of
studying. Then do another five push-ups
or 1 minute 10-minute walk. Then do it
again. Then do some something else. Lift
some weights. Do something different.
Break the pattern of Netflix and
whatever rabbit hole you're getting
into. Don't do anything with a screen.
Do something out there. That could be a
good solution. Okay, try it out, sir.
All the best. Make it work.
Rohit Shrar says, "How badly do you
think India has been impacted by its
failure to industry lies?" Modi is doing
some things, but is it too late? Can
India still build a strong manufacturing
base? I think India can still build a
strong manufacturing base. We will need
massive reforms in the ease of doing
business. Cut down the red tape. Cut
down the alleged corruption. Make energy
cheaper.
The price of energy in India is so much
higher than China, Russia, US, etc.
Electricity, make it cheaper.
Cut down all the all the red tape and
all the
license whatever the hell exists right
all the unnecessary broker brokery all
that make it easy to run a business make
it easy to start a business
whatever problems exist cut them down
make it easy for people to acquire
capital acquire funding start a business
try fail start try again all that it's
possible
India can industrialize
and obviously India has massively
impacted by its failure to
industrialize. We should have
industrialized in the 1950s.
We did not. But it's not too late. Modi
is doing things. He's building massive
infrastructure, roads, railways,
airports, whatnot. But um we need to
industrialize. Yeah, I agree. It needs
to happen. It can be done. It will need
reforms.
Aries manticors, bloated primary
education systems of the world
collapsing on themselves, producing
extremely mediocre students. Almost all
of these are west derived infiltrated by
infiltrated by vocism DEI. Is it a
coincidence? No, it's not a coincidence.
Um, it's not a coincidence. The quality
of education worldwide is going down.
The US education system is pretty poor
now compared to what they had in the
1950s. In the 1950s, they had the
world's best education system, high
quality education system. And since
then, it's been going down, down, down,
and out. Right now, it's pretty bad. But
it's still leagues ahead of India. Then
you have other education systems across
the world that are kind of going down.
Chinese education system is getting
better and better.
So you see this happening in the west.
They are dumbing their people down. They
want sheep. They don't want original
thinkers. They want people who obey.
Right? You're seeing a big brother in
action. George Orwell 1984. You see that
in action. It's not a coincidence. The
West wants just sheep to rule over. So
this is now showing us what the west
really is. It's an authoritarian system
masquerading for the longest time as a
benevolent
you know uh democratic system and all
that. We are seeing it in seeing it now
seeing it for what it is.
Okay. Aayush Gupta says can't we launch
military satellites with Russia? I
suppose we can.
It'll cost us. See, why don't we why do
we prefer to launch our own satellites,
whether it's military or whatever?
Because it's cheap.
We build our rockets and we launch the
satellites full freedom, no constraints,
no nothing. When somebody else launches
satellites for us, they'll charge money
and they'll they'll charge more than
what it costs to launch the satellites
ourselves, right? So, ideally, we should
only launch we should launch our
satellites to our own rockets only.
gives us full freedom, full sovereignty
or whatever we're doing.
So that's that's the reason why of of
course we can use Russian rockets,
American rockets. We sometimes use
SpaceX rockets because they're very
cheap, but we can also use Russian
rockets in that in that case.
AVMG
says, "Uh, thoughts on ARR?" What's ARR?
Uh, Ar Raman Arman's recent comments.
People elevated him to god-like status.
Yet he chose to play victim and show his
true colors. Well, what are my thoughts?
Never liked him. This may be
this may be unpopular. What I'm going to
going to say, I think he's mediocre as a
musician. What he's good at is
electronic music. In the 1990s, Indian
music, Bollywood music and film music
was all uh Indian instruments. And Raman
brought in the synthesizers and all the
western instruments, electronic
instruments, and he makes the music
sound great, but he's not original. He's
he's a good sound engineer, music
engineer. He's not a great musician.
He's an overrated singer. He's mediocre
and I don't like his singing and and I
don't don't like his music. Nothing to
do with his background or whatever. I
just don't I understand music, okay? I
understand what music is.
I have a back I have a musical
background myself. So so I understand
what music is and there's nothing
special about Raman. Mediocre average
guy and his recent comments is a whole
different story. I personally I've never
liked him. I said this in in 2021 or
something and people I had a big
backlash. Well, here we are today. I
stand by my words. He's mediocre and
overrated. So I'll just comment about
what I think of him as a musician. The
rest I think everyone can see what he
is.
AKS Baga says WSJ Wall Street Journal
reports just 30 minutes ago that China's
general top general leaked nuclear
secrets to the US. Well, that's
fascinating. Let's see. Um, Wall Street
Journal, China
general. What does it say?
China's she places top general under
investigation. alleged severe violations
of party discipline state laws. No, no,
no, no. I want Aha.
China's top general
accused of giving nuclear secrets to the
US. Bribery allegations and oh my
goodness, he is in deep, deep trouble.
This is a serious purge. Okay, thank you
for bringing this to my notice. So, she
is going after this
like he's totally going after this guy.
This guy is doomed. So yeah, like I
said, uh, Chinese politics is cutthroat.
I don't know if he actually did that,
but yeah. Well, he's done. His his his
goose is cooked.
Hyphen 6552 says, "I was very good at
math. I had to quit my education after
SSC because I started working early in
my life. I'm 48 now. I want to restart
learning maths. I don't know where to
begin. Any suggestions?" I'll tell you
what. The best way to learn maths is
through self-study is by using the Shom
series books. Okay. So we you start with
Shom.
Oh man, come on. Tom elementary
mathematics. This is the first book you
start. You just it will teach you the
basics. You just work through all the
pro problems. How do you learn math? You
learn math by solving problems. That's
the only way you learn mathematics.
There's no other way of learning
mathematics. and sham the sham books are
the ideal way of learning mathematics
self-study. So you start with elementary
mathematics then you go to elementary
algebra okay you go through all the
problems here then you go into um sh's u
then you go into geometry
then once you're done with geometry I
suppose you go into trigonometry
uh sorry
trig
trigonometry there we have it you go go
for this one then you go with
pre-calculus
uh shows pre-calculus then you go with
calculus and so on and then when you
when you are when you are good with
algebra trigonometry geometry
pre-calculus calculus well I think then
you can do it your own way whichever way
you want to go that's how you do it the
sham series set of books is the best
book best series of books for
mathematics you don't need anything else
so this is you know the kind of math you
would want to use in physics if you want
to go into into number theory and all
well there are different books for that
but I'm assuming you are talking about
the standard maths that I mean a
physicist would eventually use so that's
what you do
okay sir all the best I'm I'm glad that
somebody wants to actually learn math at
the age of 48 why not why not
outstanding I love it all the best sir
do well
dark Orion says the babus won't strike
if reforms are done
if if reforms are done.
I continued
the babos will strike. I am pretty sure
they will and they won't allow reforms
to happen if it if it impacts them and
their interests. That's what I expect.
Okay. Baskar Bandit says, "What are the
qualities of an excellent diplomat and
statesman? Any examples of such which
you might have admired?" I look
diplomats are tools.
diplomats are are are minions of the
people who really do the things. Uh um
and of course you
we the world has seen some some really
high quality diplomats you know who made
a big impact uh in the on the world. Um
obviously Henry Kissinger is a great
example and uh
who was the guy Napoleon's uh foreign
minister forget his name uh Napoleon's
foreign minister uh
halo
this guy he is another uh very famous
diplomat very accomplished diplomat and
was great at at his
So what are the qualities of an of an
excellent diplomat? See diplomat and
statesmen are totally different things.
A stateman statesman is a world leader.
That's a totally different thing from
being a diplomat. Totally different set
of skills. A diplomat is somebody who's
a great communicator, great negotiator,
somebody who's loyal and faithful to the
boss,
someone who's loyal and faithful to the
country, and someone who can use various
who understands what power is, what
leverage is, and understands how to use
leverage in negotiations, who who is
sophisticated and suave and polite in
public and brutal in private, and so on.
There's plenty of qualities that go into
this, right? Um, somebody who can take
pressure, somebody who can take threats,
who can convey pressure and threats and
so on. So, okay.
Mang Kosher
says, is a black hole an object or a
pathway? As far as we know, it's a black
it's an object. Um, there are some
theories that black holes could be
pathways and so on. But look, the
standard solutions to the Einstein field
equations say that you have a black hole
is a region in spaceime that conceals a
essentially a singularity at the center.
A singularity is a region of space of
spaceime that has infinite curvature and
infinite density which is obviously
unphysical but yeah that's the solution
but those are the solutions to Einstein
field equations typically this schwarz
shield solution and so on. So these are
objects not pathways. Of course you can
have something like the Einstein Rosen
Bridge which is a pathway. That's uh the
Einstein Rosen Bridge is colloially
known as a wormhole. That's a pathway
but that's a pathway that snaps shut.
You know it wants to snap shut. Doesn't
want to stay open. The the neck closes
and and splits to two black holes. How
do you keep it open? Well, that's a big
question. You can either use exotic
matter such as u negative mass matter or
you could use not even antimatter. No,
negative matter with negative mass with
repulsive gravity could potentially keep
that open if if such matter even exists.
Or you could use something like a cosmic
string which is a topological defect in
the fabric of spacetime itself and so
on. So a black hole is an object. It's
not a pathway.
Basar Bandit says 396 Russian drones hit
Kiev yesterday. It's the second day of
talks in the UAE. Will this round end
the same as before? US pushing and
Zillinsky not backing off. Nothing's
going to change. Nothing. Yeah. This
this this round of talks is not going to
produce any any results.
Yeah. I don't see that happening. I I
hope I'm wrong. I hope there is some
some ceasefire or something. But no.
Zalinski Zalinski his life depends on
the war continuing.
How why will he back off? Yeah. So yeah,
I don't see anything happening at this
point in time. Pascar Bandit says,
"Muggals or muggles?" Muggles. Muggles.
M U G. Muggles.
And I think that was the last of the
questions for today. It's been 3 and 1/2
hours. Nearly three and a half hours.
Well, that brings me to the end of
episode 325 of Ask a Bijit. Thank you so
much everybody for all the questions. It
was as always great fun. I look forward
to continuing this next week in the
episodes that we have. We will have next
weekend. So, I look forward to see you
there. Keep learning my friends. Keep
learning, keep being positive,
keep asking questions, and keep raising
your standards. Take care. I'll see you
very soon in the next one. Bye-bye for
now.